<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-05-28T14:36:35-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">avisuj</title><subtitle>Avi Sujeeth&apos;s personal blog. This blog captures my adventures  trying to guide my family through the 21st century. It&apos;s my hope  that it&apos;ll help me lead an intentional life and one day provide some  inspiration for my children&apos;s adventures.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Dual Nature of Human Thinking: Integrating Intuition and Deliberation for Success</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/parenting/The-Dual-Nature-of-Human-Thinking/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Dual Nature of Human Thinking: Integrating Intuition and Deliberation for Success" /><published>2023-04-14T01:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-04-14T01:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/parenting/The-Dual-Nature-of-Human-Thinking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/parenting/The-Dual-Nature-of-Human-Thinking/">&lt;p&gt;I am currently reading the Art of Possibility by Rosamund Stone Zander, a counselor, and Benjamin Zander, a conductor and teacher.  They talk about two selves: the measuring self and the full self. The measuring self is concerned with how you compare to others and how you measure up to external standards. The full self is concerned with your own internal standards and values.  They provide 12 practices such as “It’s all invented”, “Giving an A”, and “The Way Things Are” that can help you change your perspective in order to see new possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over Easter, I related how Mr. Zander manifested his practice of “Giving an A” at New England Conservatory of Music by literally giving his students an A in exchange for a detailed paper describing what they did to deserve an A - an exercise that forces the students to articulate their internal goals are.  His point is that the measuring self can be limiting.  In a similar way, Carol Dweck describes the concept of mindset and how it affects our lives.  Her book, Mindset, argues that people have either a fixed mindset or a growth mindset. A fixed mindset is one in which people believe that their abilities are fixed and cannot be changed. A growth mindset is one in which people believe that their abilities can be developed through hard work and dedication. The book argues that people with a growth mindset are more likely to succeed in life because they are more willing to take risks and learn from their mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet when I found myself taking about Art of Possibility - I found myself hedging the explanation.  Maybe “Giving an A” only applied when you were dealing with top performers, like musicians studying at the New England Conservatory of Music.  “Giving an A” is about believing the best about the other people you interact with.  When we believe the best about others we open ourselves up to their feedback, that feedback gives us opportunities to learn, learning helps us embrace new possibilities.  Indeed, it’s similar to the idea of rejecting victim stories presented in Thanks for Feedback by Douglas Stone and Sheila Heen.  A victim story makes us out to be innocent sufferers in the predicament while a villain story helps us justify any negative action we take toward the other by attributing evil or malicious motives. In order to receive feedback, we have to realize that they aren’t villains&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like then the concept has broad application.  So why did I hedge?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more I read about human psychology, the more impressed I am with how brain operates in dual modes.  In Thinking Fast and Slow, Daniel Kahneman describes two systems that drive the way we think: System 1 is fast, intuitive, and emotional; System 2 is slower, more deliberative, and more logical.  While both modes have purpose, sometimes we are served in intentionally shifting the mode we are in.  Tying back to the Art of Possibility:  I see the calculating self as deliberative and logical and the full self as intuitive and emotional.  The Art of Possibility then is making the case that to embrace possibility we have to shift our state to System 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that there are times when it makes sense to embrace our intuitive and emotional self.  Yet while I was related the story, I found myself wondering is it really fair to give everyone an A?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fairness, like many amorphous topics, is multifaceted and includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consistency: A decision is considered fair if it is consistent with established rules, norms, and procedures. If a decision is arbitrary or made on the basis of personal biases, it may be considered unfair.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Impartiality: A decision is considered fair if it is made without bias or prejudice towards any particular individual or group. This means that the decision-maker must be neutral and objective, and must not favor one group or individual over another.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transparency: A decision is considered fair if the decision-making process is transparent and open to scrutiny. This means that the decision-maker must be willing to explain their reasoning and provide clear justifications for the decision.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accessibility: A decision is considered fair if it is accessible to all affected parties. This means that all parties must have equal access to information and resources that are relevant to the decision.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consequences: A decision is considered fair if its consequences are distributed fairly and equitably among all affected parties. This means that the decision should not disproportionately benefit or harm any particular individual or group.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Participation: A decision is considered fair if all affected parties have the opportunity to participate in the decision-making process. This means that all parties must have the opportunity to express their views and have their voices heard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Giving an A” is inconsistent with how I understand school triggering my concern.  At the same time, it met every other criteria.  In the end, the process appeared to result in better outcomes for the students in the class.  Sometimes, I think we need to break the rules in order to get out of the box that we are in.  In this scenario, trying to help students to embrace their mastery, “Giving an A” makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reflection, I think:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We work in two ways: fast intuitive and emotional AND slower, deliberative and logical.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When we are trying to explore the unknown, our intuitive and emotional self can help us hear feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When we are trying to improve, our slower deliberative and logical self can help us process feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By integrating both processes and embracing mistakes, we learn.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We should be mindful of how our actions affect others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ultimately hedged because it’s not always right to “Give an A”.  Sometimes it’s important to be able to measure performance to get a picture of the way things are so that you can improve.  Likewise, sometimes it’s important to set that aside so you can break through to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="integrity" /><category term="heart" /><category term="parenting" /><summary type="html">The blog post discusses the concept of &apos;Giving an A&apos; from the book &apos;The Art of Possibility&apos; by Rosamund Stone Zander and Benjamin Zander, and how it relates to the dual modes of thinking in the brain. Embracing both fast, intuitive, and emotional thinking and slower, deliberative, and logical thinking is important for learning and growth.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring the Intersection of AI and Human Values: Opportunities, Challenges, and Ethics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/technology/Exploring-the-Intersection-of-AI-and-Human-Values-Opportunities-Challenges-Ethics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring the Intersection of AI and Human Values: Opportunities, Challenges, and Ethics" /><published>2023-04-08T01:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-04-08T01:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/technology/Exploring-the-Intersection-of-AI-and-Human-Values-Opportunities-Challenges-Ethics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/technology/Exploring-the-Intersection-of-AI-and-Human-Values-Opportunities-Challenges-Ethics/">&lt;p&gt;I’m starting to use ChatGPT to summarize documents, plan my summer vacation, and write blog posts.  It’s been an amazing assistant that I’m going to put to the test as I try to do even more with the same finite time I have available.  It’s given me an intermediary choice between outsourcing an activity and doing it myself; getting automated assistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, this summer we are planning a vacation from Miami to Bar Harbor Maine.  I think I’ll be an amazing experience taking us through ten cities on the east coast - through national parks, museums, cities and landmarks in thirty days.  Initially, Missy and I set target locations and decided on potential dates.  After, I used ChatGPT to generate suggestions about specific itinerary that we should do in each location.  In combination with packaged tours, we were able to get to an itinerary that is tailored to us.  Because we had control, I was able to leverage loyalty programs that we have with Enterprise, Marriott, and Amtrak to maximize our benefits.  Because I value that control, I’ve taken the role of a travel agent for the trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial intelligence (AI) is the ability of machines to perform tasks that normally require human intelligence, such as reasoning, learning, decision making, and creativity. AI has been advancing rapidly in recent years, thanks to the availability of large amounts of data, powerful computing resources, and innovative algorithms. AI has also been applied to various domains and industries, such as health care, education, entertainment, finance, security, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI has brought many benefits and opportunities to humanity, such as improving efficiency, productivity, quality, and innovation. However, AI also poses many challenges and risks, such as ethical dilemmas, social impacts, legal issues, and existential threats. How can we ensure that AI is used for good and not evil? How can we balance the benefits and risks of AI? How can we respect human values and dignity in the age of AI?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently read Moonwalking with Einstein by Joshua Foer.  In the book, Foer recounts how he became interested in memory training and over the course of a year became the US memory champion.  Memory training was once a critical part in education.  As we started relying on writing and later devices to help our memory, memory training became impractical.  Even so, it feels like there was something that was lost:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mere reading is not necessarily learning—a fact that I am personally confronted with every time I try to remember the contents of a book I’ve just put down. To really learn a text, one had to memorize it. As the early-eighteenth-century Dutch poet Jan Luyken put it, “One book, printed in the Heart’s own wax / Is worth a thousand in the stacks.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that’s the case with memory, what happens when you augment the way you think with artificial intelligence?  If all people possess Descartes “good sense”, the ability to distinguish truth from fiction, than do I retain my being as long as I am accountable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think these questions are important because they touch upon the core of what makes us human. As humans, we have a unique capacity to think critically, creatively, and ethically. We have a unique ability to reflect on ourselves and our actions. We have a unique responsibility to act according to our moral values and principles. We have a unique dignity that deserves respect and protection. We have a unique solidarity that binds us together as a community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these human qualities are not fixed or static. They are dynamic and evolving. They are influenced by our environment and our interactions with others. They are also influenced by our tools and technologies. As Marshall McLuhan famously said: “We shape our tools and thereafter our tools shape us.” This means that the technologies we use can affect how we think, feel, and act. They can also affect how we perceive ourselves and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethical artificial intelligence is a topic that concerns how humans and machines interact with each other in a way that respects human values, rights, and dignity. It also involves the moral principles and guidelines that should inform the design, development, and deployment of AI systems, as well as the accountability and responsibility of those who create and use them. Some of the main ethical principles of AI are transparency, fairness, non-maleficence, beneficence, privacy, trust, sustainability, dignity, and solidarity . These principles aim to ensure that AI systems are aligned with human interests and values, and do not cause harm or injustice to individuals or society . Ethical AI is important because it can have significant impacts on various aspects of human life, such as health, education, work, security, and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the potential of the unknown will drive further exploration.  While we are walking the path, we will learn how our creation affects us - if it leads us to harness more knowledge or instead reinforce our vices.  In truth, it will probably do both.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="integrity" /><category term="heart" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html">This blog post explores the intersection of artificial intelligence (AI) and human values, including the benefits and risks of AI, the impact of AI on human qualities and dignity, and the importance of ethical AI. It discusses the potential of AI to augment human capabilities, but also the need to ensure that AI is aligned with human interests and values and does not cause harm or injustice. Ultimately, it highlights the dynamic and evolving nature of human qualities and the role of technology in shaping them, and calls for a responsible and reflective approach to the design, development, and use of AI systems.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Living an Agile Life: Coping with Unknown Unknowns</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/integrity/parenting/Living-an-Agile-Life-Coping-with-Unknown-Unknowns/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Living an Agile Life: Coping with Unknown Unknowns" /><published>2023-04-07T01:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-04-07T01:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/integrity/parenting/Living-an-Agile-Life-Coping-with-Unknown-Unknowns</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/integrity/parenting/Living-an-Agile-Life-Coping-with-Unknown-Unknowns/">&lt;p&gt;On the precipice of the Iraq Invasion, Donald Rumsfeld, the former US Secretary of Defense, said that there are three types of things in the world:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Known knowns: These are things that we know that we know. For example, we know that the Earth is round and that water is wet.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Known unknowns: These are things that we know that we don’t know. For example, we don’t know when the next earthquake will happen or who will win the next election.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unknown unknowns: These are things that we don’t know that we don’t know. These are the most unpredictable and surprising things that can happen. For example, we didn’t know that a pandemic would hit the world in 2020 or that a new variant of the virus would emerge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unknown unknowns are future outcomes, events, circumstances, or consequences that we cannot predict. We cannot plan for them either. We don’t even know when and where to search for them. They pose a potentially greater risk simply because they cannot be anticipated based on past experience or investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I look into the future, it feels like I’m surrounded with unknown unknowns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will the world order hold&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will there be nuclear war&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will artificial intelligence disrupt society&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s ok not to know the future.  In software development, the agile process was created to handle the unknown unknowns. Agile is a method of software development that was created to handle complex and uncertain projects. It’s based on four principles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deliver value early and often: Instead of waiting for a perfect product or solution, agile teams deliver small, testable, and valuable features or ideas in short cycles called sprints. This way, they can get feedback from customers or users and improve their product or solution quickly and continuously.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Embrace change: Instead of resisting or fearing change, agile teams welcome it as an opportunity to learn and grow. They are flexible and responsive to changing requirements, market conditions, customer needs, and feedback. They also experiment with new ideas and technologies to find better ways of doing things.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collaborate: Instead of working in silos or hierarchies, agile teams work together as self-organizing and cross-functional units. They communicate openly and frequently with each other and with their stakeholders. They also share their knowledge, skills, and resources to achieve their common goals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reflect and improve: Instead of repeating the same mistakes or sticking to the same habits, agile teams reflect on their performance and processes regularly. They identify what works well and what needs improvement. They also take action to implement changes and measure their impact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach lets you adjust to changing environment by taking moments to recalibrate the plan from things you’ve learned.  Those micro-adjustments can make a world of difference in achieving a goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that agile is not only a way of developing software but also a way of living life. It can help us cope with unknown unknowns by making us more adaptable, creative, and resilient.  That’s why I have adopted agile as my personal philosophy and practice. I have set some goals for myself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to get into better shape&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to retire in Hawaii&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to see my kids be successful&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to make difference in the world through my work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to start a scholarship to inspire others to live their best lives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have to tackle all the things at once, but I can set goals like how much I need to have saved to retire to Hawaii or start the scholarship fund.  And I can look for opportunities to start things earlier.  For example, I’m investigating what it would take to start awarding a $5K annual scholarship right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By living my life as close to the present as I can, I get to savor simple pleasures, focus on today’s actions, and embrace opportunities as they appear.  Reflecting on how I’ve done monthly, I can ensure that I am connecting what I’m doing with my long term goals.  In addition, I try to periodically look up to determine if I’m still happy with where I think I’m going.  When the world flips on its head, I hope this approach will allow me to adapt to the changes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="integrity" /><category term="parenting" /><summary type="html">This blog post explores the concept of unknown unknowns and how they can impact our lives. It discusses the agile methodology as a way of coping with uncertainties and achieving personal goals. By breaking down goals into smaller tasks, embracing change, collaborating, and reflecting, we can better adapt to unknowns and live our best lives.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unpacking the Meaning of Value: Why Innate Worth Outlasts Job Titles</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/legacy/parenting/Unpacking-the-Meaning-of-Value-Why-Innate-Worth-Outlasts-Job-Titles/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unpacking the Meaning of Value: Why Innate Worth Outlasts Job Titles" /><published>2023-02-18T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-02-18T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/legacy/parenting/Unpacking-the-Meaning-of-Value-Why-Innate-Worth-Outlasts-Job-Titles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/legacy/parenting/Unpacking-the-Meaning-of-Value-Why-Innate-Worth-Outlasts-Job-Titles/">&lt;p&gt;It’s layoff season.  While this round, I’m safe - I’ve been let go twice in my career so far.  The first time I laid off it was jarring for me because I defined my value by my job.  Clearly, I’m more than my job.  I’m also a son, husband, father, community member, volunteer, church goer, gym member, mentor, and friend.  I have many roles.  I’ve come to realize value doesn’t come from a role.  I think value is endowed by our creator - as the declaration of independence says “all men are created equal, that they are endowed by their Creator with certain unalienable rights, that among these are Life, Liberty and the Pursuit of happiness.”  Besides our innate value, I think value is also bestowed by others.  I’ve come to believe that bestowed value is transient while innate value is permanent and real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;sources-of-value&quot;&gt;Sources of Value&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Value is a measure of worth.  It is observable.  I think an individual’s value comes from:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being Human&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Providing Economic Value&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leading Others&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Protecting Others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;innate-value&quot;&gt;Innate Value&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our core value is rooted in our humanity; in our connections, potential, and connectedness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have connections with each other.  Everyone is a son, daughter, mother, or father.  Those connections can be established via blood or through deepened relationships.  Individuals are cherished and that demands respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have untold potential.  Today we stand on the shoulder’s of those who came before us through an arc of history that has seen life expectancy rise, wealth grow, and peace expand.  Moreover, we have control over our destiny - through our choices and our efforts we can change the path we are on.  Never underestimate a fellow human; instead show reverence because one day a human will solve a problem that today is impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are connected with each other through empathy.  Our emotions connect us.  “The sadness from which compassion springs is a pro-social emotion, an agent of connection and love” (Bittersweet).  When you see another person, try to see yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bestowed-value&quot;&gt;Bestowed Value&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other sources of value result from our inter personal interactions.  We ascribe value to those who provide service.  In Leaders Eat Last, Simon Sinek relates that hierarchy was established to promote societal order.  Sinek continues that a leaders value is rooted in their ability to serve the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This premise is echoed through anecdote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every great company starts by solving an important problem. (Startup.com)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The best test as a leader is: Do those served grow as persons; do they become healthier, wiser, freer, more autonomous, more likely themselves to become leaders? (Robert Greenleaf)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being a soldier is more than courage; it’s sacrificing yourself for something greater than yourself. (Anonymous)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We pay, honor, and respect those who provide service.  However, this value is ultimately fleeting.  Rich have become poor.  Politicians have become criminals.  Veterans have become homeless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because bestowed value can lead to inequity, it can be easy to covet.  In warning, Simon Sinek points out that a false leader will struggle to hold on to their position once they’ve got it because the value of leadership comes from the people. “It is nice to be important, but it’s more important to be nice.” (Walter Winchell)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;lasting-value&quot;&gt;Lasting Value&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Power of Positivity, the regrets of people on their deathbed are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Didn’t spend enough time with their family.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wasn’t kind, patient, or loving enough.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Should’ve taken more risks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Didn’t express their feelings to loved ones or themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Didn’t forgive when their was time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we face death, it’s not bestowed value we treasure.  Instead we focus on our innate value and the innate value of those closest to us.  If there’s a lesson here, I think it’s to appreciate each person as God given.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="integrity" /><category term="heart" /><category term="legacy" /><category term="parenting" /><summary type="html">This post explores the true sources of value in human life, distinguishing between innate value, which is rooted in our humanity and connections with others, and bestowed value, which is based on economic or social status. I argue that appreciating and valuing each person as God-given is key to recognizing and honoring our own innate worth and that of others.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Frustrated with My Health; Trying to Trust The Process</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/Frustration-Trust-The-Process/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Frustrated with My Health; Trying to Trust The Process" /><published>2023-01-02T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-01-02T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/Frustration-Trust-The-Process</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/Frustration-Trust-The-Process/">&lt;p&gt;My post on the new year doesn’t adequately capture the frustration I feel around 2022.  I did the right things but indicators around my health are neutral at best.  Compared to 2021, I was 45% more active.  How is it that you can exercise more yet have many of the signals of your cardio vascular age (hrv, cholesterol, lipids) fall out of control?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, it’s a signal of one of few possibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m working on the wrong things with regards to my health.  In effect, I’m trying to climb the wrong mountain.  As I’m reflecting on my progress, I’m frustrated because I’m not where I thought I’d be.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I haven’t given the process enough time to work.  Progress isn’t linear and it’s easy to get frustrated when results of effort aren’t visible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m working on things poorly.  Bad practice leads to middling results.  Good practice leads to perfection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;working-on-the-wrong-things&quot;&gt;Working on the Wrong Things&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Seven Habits of Highly Effective People, Steven Covey relates a story of two groups of producers who are working they’re we through a jungle.  A leader is the one who climbs a tree, surveys the entire situation, and shouts “Wrong Jungle”.  Managers respond by saying “But, we’re making progress.”  According to Covey, “Effectiveness - often even survival - does not depend solely on how much effort we expand, but on whether or not the effort we spend is in the right jungle.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My health reports should be viewed as signals; understanding what the signals mean is important.  I’m confident they aren’t telling me to exercise less.  According to the American Heart Association, people who exercise at least 150 minutes a week materially reduce their risk of heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, exercise alone may not be enough.  According to (CNET)[https://www.cnet.com/health/fitness/how-to-get-a-six-pack-with-diet-and-exercise/], “No matter how strong your ab muscles are, they’re not going to show through unless you have a low enough body fat.”  Body fat results from eating a calorie surplus - the excess calories get stored as body fat.  The last time I made significant progress at reducing my body fat was when I tracked my meals via MyFitnessPal.  Working from home means I take less steps and I’m surrounded by food.  Even when I’m exerting some self-control, it’s easy for me to unconsciously run a calorie surplus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The message I’m hearing from my health reports is that I need to track what I eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;progress-isnt-linear&quot;&gt;Progress isn’t Linear&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People imagine progress as  a straight line up and to right.  As time marches, you make steady progress towards the goal.  The reality is much of different because the journey to success is full of learning.  What works?  What doesn’t?  In addition, we live in complex systems and things outside of control can have affect.  Are there new stressors?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-theme=&quot;dark&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Progress Isn&amp;#39;t Linear - &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/LqGTXFkp4q&quot;&gt;https://t.co/LqGTXFkp4q&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/sVQOk5IF5r&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/sVQOk5IF5r&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; avisuj (@avisuj) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/avisuj/status/1610054108219678721?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;January 2, 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve learned that instead of measuring progress as achievement to a goal, it’s better to measure learning.  Life is an experiment, if you learn from the shots you take you will eventually make a basket.  Further signal doesn’t always mean insight.  For example, I’m obviously frustrated with my cardiovascular health.  If I took that signal to mean that I should dramatically change my work out - I may creating more damage than benefit.  After all, doing something imperfect consistently is more likely to result in progress than doing the perfect thing occasionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ed Camult shares in Creativity that Pixar has a maxim “Trust the Process”.  While Ed’s talking about the process that Pixar setup for story review, I think can be applied to any process that follows the scientific method.  Learning is the outcome of observing, forming a hypothesis, running an experiment, and submitting for a peer review.  That type of process helps you learn which makes you better at what you pursue over a long enough time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I haven’t been at this long enough.  In fact, after I’ve made the changes to my diet I found that my HRV scores recently have doubled!  Implementing small changes from learnings can result in progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;bad-practice&quot;&gt;Bad Practice&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Peak, Anders Erickson relates a story of how we learn.  When we want to learn a new skill like Tennis, we practice until it becomes automatic.  While we still have weaknesses, we stop improving because we aren’t deliberate.  We’re practicing things we’re good at rather than what our weaknesses are.  To overcome this obstacle, Erickson states it’s important to have well defined goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I certainly am not a professional weight lifter or cyclist.  It very well could be that I’m not seeing health improvements because I’m not doing the right activities.  For example, my cycling time hasn’t materially improved over the last year.  Likewise, I’m lifting a bit less weight than I used to lift two years ago.  I probably could get better outcomes if I saw a personal trainer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal isn’t to be professional cyclist or lifter.  Instead, I want to increase my health span and do more of what I enjoy.  To that end, I am partnering with a physician who specialized in precision health.  I think they’ll be able to help me understand if it would be worthwhile to invest in a trainer or if a different experiment is more promising.  My first appointment is February 6th.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="integrity" /><category term="heart" /><summary type="html">My post on the new year doesn&apos;t adequately capture the frustration I feel around 2022. I did the right things but indicators around my health are neutral at best. Compared to 2021, I was 45% more active. How is it that you can exercise more yet have many of the signals of your cardio vascular age (hrv, cholesterol, lipids) fall out of control?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Looking Back at 2022: Year in Review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/integrity/investing/legacy/tech/Looking-Back-at-2022-Year-in-Review/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Looking Back at 2022: Year in Review" /><published>2022-12-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-12-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/integrity/investing/legacy/tech/Looking-Back-at-2022-Year-in-Review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/integrity/investing/legacy/tech/Looking-Back-at-2022-Year-in-Review/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t do 2022 differently, but there are definitely some changes I want to take into 2023.  Over the year, we made some great memories.  Financially, we were even with the market.  Given the market stress and significant one time expenses, I’m impressed with how our new budgeting system is working.  I wish we would have adopted it sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professionally, I couldn’t be happier with the job move into Patient experience.  I’m hopeful that the work I’ve put in will become visible through customer success communicated via case studies shortly.  I feel like I’m making a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going forward to 2023, I’m going to watch what I eat more carefully.  In addition, we need to be more accountable to our travel budget.  This year was ok, I hope next year is even better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;notable-events&quot;&gt;Notable Events&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;European Vacation - This year we went on amazing vacation through central Europe.  We were able to cross ten cities and eleven countries by train.  Notable memories include: a gondola in Venice, an opera in Prague, and the Ann Frank House.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thanksgiving Vacation - We visited the Grand Canyon with Missy’s parents.  It was the first time the kids got to see the Grand Canyon.  Afterwards, we spent a few days in Huntington Beach by the Ocean.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Passing of Todd Fujawa - Todd’s a friend.  His daughter and Abby are friends.  His sudden passing was a surprise that hit too close to home.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Death of Hedwig - Missy totaled our Chrysler Pacifica and we ended up purchasing another one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;wellness&quot;&gt;Wellness&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the year, I’ve gained 12 pounds while I’ve lost 2” around my waist.  I was 25% more active than last year contributing to increased muscle mass.  At the same token, I’m approaching my 2018 weight.  My health markers reflect it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My cholesterol and lipid levels are as high as 2018.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My resting heart beat has increased three beats per minute.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My fitness level score decreased by two points.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 2023, I need to get my weight under control.  As such, I’m restarting logging my food.  If I want to eat it, I need to log it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;finances&quot;&gt;Finances&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year the bubble burst.  In addition, we spent $74K more than last year.  In total, we lost 15% of our net worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our top three spending categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$54K Automotive - replacing a car&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$43K Taxes - underpayment on last year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$38K Travel - $13K over budget&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ignoring the above spending categories, expenses were within expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s also important to view 2022 in context of the broader market.  The benchmarks of SPY and CoinGecko were down 20% and 62% respectively.  Broadly, our investments asset classes performed at par with benchmarks.  As a result of the bear market, our investments have been concentrated in stock equities.  In addition passive income is only slightly growing.  Getting to a balanced ratio is going to take intentional saving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A notable success is that our credit card balances were low throughout the year.  The new budgeting system I’ve put in place that forecasts episodic expenses and saves for them via dedicated accounts has proven to be remarkably successful.  I think prepaying our expenses is the heart of “pay yourself first” and really helped improve our resiliency throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;sustainability&quot;&gt;Sustainability&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our electricity usage was flat at 21,500 kWh.  Excluding AC, the largest consumers were dehumidifier, car, and garage fan.  Going forward, we’re going to use the dehumidifier and garage fan less.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our natural gas usage was flat at 390 CCF.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="integrity" /><category term="investing" /><category term="legacy" /><category term="tech" /><summary type="html">I wouldn&apos;t do 2022 differently, but there are definitely some changes I want to take into 2023. Over the year, we made some great memories. Financially, we were even with the market. Given the market stress and significant one time expenses, I&apos;m impressed with how our new budgeting system is working. I wish we would have adopted it sooner.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Death and Dying</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/faith/heart/On-Death-and-Dying/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Death and Dying" /><published>2022-11-21T16:57:59-06:00</published><updated>2022-11-21T16:57:59-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/faith/heart/On-Death-and-Dying</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/faith/heart/On-Death-and-Dying/">&lt;p&gt;As I lit our gas fireplace last night, the flames seemed to dance.  But just as quickly as they came alive, they would snuff out as the fuel exhausted.  Dead.  I think this impermanence lends to the flames beauty.  Demands attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend of the family passed away last night.  He left behind his wife, two daughters (20 and 12) and a son (9).  His middle child and Abby are friends.  Dead.  Sometimes life isn’t fair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully in my last episode of depression, I went deep on grief:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Its-That-Youre-Not-Understand-ebook/dp/B073XXYKLP/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=it%27s+ok+that+you%27re+not+ok&amp;amp;qid=1669070005&amp;amp;s=digital-text&amp;amp;sprefix=it%27s+ok+%2Cdigital-text%2C204&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot;&gt;It’s OK that You’re NOT OK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Sanctuary-Memoir-Emily-Rapp-Black-ebook/dp/B087BCBNWW/ref=sr_1_1?crid=18Z9SZIEPT2RC&amp;amp;keywords=sanctuary+a+memoir&amp;amp;qid=1669070037&amp;amp;s=digital-text&amp;amp;sprefix=sanctuary+a+memoir%2Cdigital-text%2C164&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot;&gt;Sanctuary: a Memoir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Shame-Interrupted-Lifts-Worthlessness-Rejection-ebook/dp/B007WWB990/ref=sr_1_1?crid=YFO9OGB5KQ9A&amp;amp;keywords=shame+interrupted&amp;amp;qid=1669070061&amp;amp;s=digital-text&amp;amp;sprefix=shame+interrupted%2Cdigital-text%2C160&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot;&gt;Shame Interrupted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I watched &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l2zLCCRT-nE&quot;&gt;Refuge in Grief&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Bittersweet-Sorrow-Longing-Make-Whole/dp/B09BW27GLR/ref=sr_1_1?crid=12PVST2871E1S&amp;amp;keywords=bittersweet&amp;amp;qid=1669070193&amp;amp;sprefix=bittersweet%2Caps%2C202&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;Bittersweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned that Grief is a natural reaction to Love that was taken away.  Grief cannot be fixed and it has no timeline.  Most people react to grief by trying to make it better.  You can never bring back my friends husband.  Sometimes people try to compare grief.  There’s no award for sadness.  In fact, the best way to address grief is to witness it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadness is interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Sadness triggers compassion.  It brings people together. . . The word compassion literally means ‘to suffer&lt;br /&gt;
together’ . . . The sadness from which compassion springs is a pro-social emotion, an agent of connection and
love; it’s what the musician Nick Cave calls ‘the universal unifying force.’  Sorrow and tears are one of the
strongest bonding mechanisms we have”  (Bittersweet, Susan Cain).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the midst of loss how do you comfort one another?  On Sunday we went to church.  Missy was mad at me because I was forcing the motions and not showing “empathy”.  In the quiet of the motions, bonding started to happen.  Prior to the service, Missy and Abby were able to quiet away a conversation on loss.  After the service, we were able to seek out prayer with a prayer leader which offered the palliative healing of confession.  Acknowledging our pain. Asking for help. Focus on what we wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In prayer I asked for the discernment to witness pain and be supportive.  To help without trying to fix the un-fixable.  To let our love be felt.  At the end of the prayer, Missy was a little misty eyed.  We also had greater appreciation of the task ahead of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After church, we ran Missy’s parents and Isaac to the house.  Abby, Missy, and myself made the trek to our friend.  There we sat, we snacked, and we talked.  Sometimes we remembered.  Sometimes we cried.  We talked about help.  We talked about space.  We hugged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the beginning of this process; but I think we were able to achieve our goal.  Now as life happens, I pray for grace that we remember what is important and keep that in the center of our life and outreach.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="faith" /><category term="heart" /><summary type="html">We recently lost a friend. More importantly our friends lost a father and a husband. In this post, I explore how the living try to continue the journey with love and compassion.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Personal Compass</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/faith/heart/Personal-Compass/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Personal Compass" /><published>2022-06-04T20:15:59-05:00</published><updated>2022-06-04T20:15:59-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/faith/heart/Personal-Compass</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/faith/heart/Personal-Compass/">&lt;p&gt;This weekend I had the opportunity to attend Pentecost mass at St. Xavier, the college church at St. Louis University.  The reflection after the mass encouraged celebrants to engage in Holy Spirit listening.  Because we’re often short of time, listening feels like a last art.  The leader of reflection related a story:  she attended a conference on listening and was reminded as our culture has embraced tribalism we’ve separated into two groups that reflect identity instead of just politics.  She recognized that she was afflicted as the speaker shared symbols associated with each group:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a MAGA cap&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a Black Lives Matter poster&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a Rainbow flag&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Confederate flag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we’re short for time, we talk in terms of labels; but like on a cup of soup, the label isn’t the same as the contents.  When we see a label we disagree with, we can stop listening especially if it triggers us.   In Thanks for the Feedback, Stone and Heen state that a common reason feedback is rejected is because it fires a truth trigger, a relationship trigger, or an identity trigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel this being liberal in Texas.  There are many times I’m at my kitchen table reminding my family that our neighbors can be good people even if they vote differently then us.  In fact, Daniel Pink shares in the Power of Regret that many of our moral differences occur “because one group has a narrower view of morality (don’t harm or cheat other people) and the other has a wider view (don’t harm or cheat other people—but also stay loyal to your group, heed authority, and uphold the sacred).”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to tap into “Holy Spirit Listening”, I think it’s very important to understand what you personally believe and to be curious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I planned for a job change earlier this year, I did some &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/my-core-values-integrity-heart-avi-sujeeth/?trackingId=Pd7VT73wG7D1OiJXKF46JA%3D%3D&quot;&gt;reflection&lt;/a&gt; on my core values: integrity and heart.  For me, it’s important to be my full-self in every aspect of my life.  When I see an apparent contradiction in my life or find others who have different values, I try to respond with curiosity - to seek to understand - to Holy Spirit Listen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve adopted framework’s across my political, religious, and science beliefs that I try glue together through rationalization into a tapestry that reflects my values.  The frameworks help me understand what I believe and what those beliefs state about my values - they become my personal compass.  Broadly I believe:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Politics is a social contract for the distribution of power.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Religion is a faith based expression of morality.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Science is a way of exploring the truth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;politics&quot;&gt;Politics&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human beings are social creatures.  In “Why Leaders Eat Last” Simon Sinek states early in our existence we learned that we were more effective with outside dangers by working together.  Through specialization and cooperation, we were able to thrive and ultimately change our conditions to suite our needs, creating a world of surplus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we went from groups of 150 people, to city states, to nations - we needed a social compact on how power was distributed.  Our political systems distribute power across dimensions of representativeness and arbitrariness.  Our economic systems distribute resources across dimensions of control and centralization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/avisuj/avisuj.github.io/blob/main/_includes/Political.JPG?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Political Quadrant Grid show Democracy (Elected, Rule of Law), Communism (Declared, Rule of Law), Fascism (Elected, Rule of Power), Dictatorship (Declared, Rule of Power)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/avisuj/avisuj.github.io/blob/main/_includes/Economic.JPG?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Economic Quadrant Grid show Socialism (Planned Economy, Distributed Economy), Capitalism (Market Economy, Distributed Economy), Aristocracy (Planned Economy, Centralized Economy), Oligarchy (Market Economy, Centralized Economy)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living in the United States, I think a governments effectiveness can be measured by the degree that it empowers all of its constituents to pursue life, liberty and happiness.  Often times, I think that means a government must be able to balance the sometimes conflicted needs of constituents in a way that is perceived as just and fair.  I believe systems that distribute power through the rule of law tend to be more resilient over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework allows me to go beyond the label associated with a government or an economic system to attempt to understand the values they represent.  When I find people who disagree with me, I try to be curious as to why they disagree:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does Communism mean something different to them?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are they advocating for the Rule of Power?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do they see a major value different between elected leaders and declared leaders?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework helps me go deeper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;religion&quot;&gt;Religion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an objectivist, I believe that moral truths exist.  I think living in alignment with these moral truths is living a Good Life. I think religion provides instruction around the moral truths and consequently makes it easier to live a Good Life.  As willing collaborators in God’s plan, we gain freedom from sin through the sacrifice of Jesus Christ.  Jesus calls us to love and in love we find our purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also think that is possible to live a Good Life by embracing a virtuous mindset regardless of faith.  For example, humanists are concerned with living a Good Life and will leverage the scientific method to reason what a Good Life looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The major religions have cultural codes that are captured in their texts, rituals, norms, and beliefs.  Rather than simply dismissing points of view I disagree with, I try to understand it in the full context of the religion.  I also try to evaluate if I think another religion more accurately describes what I believe to be morally true.   As US Bishops have started to deny communion to politicians for supporting the legalization of abortion, I’ve spent time reading the catechism, considering my beliefs, and talking to religious leaders and mentors.  In my microcosm, I have found that the Catholic Church continues to best reflect what I consider moral truth and my beliefs are also consistent with church teachings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;science&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his master class, Neil deGrasse Tyson describes the scientific method as “a problem solving approach that helps you glean reliable evidence in support of a hypothesis.”  It allows scientists to test ideas in the effort to identify the truth.  Scientists share and repeat these tests until there is no need to keep doing so.  After a test is completed, it is published in terms dictated by the scientific method:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;observation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;questions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hypothesis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;experiment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;result&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;conclusion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process allows for independent validation that roots out bias and mistakes.  I believe the truth discovered through the scientific method is useful like a landmark is to a person on voyage; it points to the right direction.  Therefore, I think it’s important to reconcile what we learn through science with my political and religious beliefs as it helps ensure that I’m actually making progress to the Good Life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to get lost in a meme.  It’s easy to respond to snark with sarcasm.  It’s much harder to learn from those that disagree with you.  It’s harder to listen with curiosity.  I use mental models as a way to deconstruct labels into implied values.  By staying curious, by leveraging the Holy Spirit to listen, I think my life is more rewarding because I can search for God in others and turn them into my teachers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="faith" /><category term="heart" /><summary type="html">It&apos;s easy to get lost in a meme. It&apos;s easy to respond to snark with sarcasm. It&apos;s much harder to learn from those that disagree with you. It&apos;s harder to listen with curiosity. In this blog post I talk about how I use mental models to deconstruct labels into implied values. By staying curious, by leveraging the Holy Spirit to listen, I think my life is more rewarding because I can search for God in others and turn them into my teachers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Communion</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/faith/parenting/Communion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Communion" /><published>2022-04-16T20:15:59-05:00</published><updated>2022-04-16T20:15:59-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/faith/parenting/Communion</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/faith/parenting/Communion/">&lt;p&gt;While I’ve talked about religion in the past, I haven’t deeply gone into my spiritual journey.  I’m going to in this post because I think it will be useful for me to resolve some apparent contradictions that from the outside maybe confusing.  For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why did I choose Catholicism when my wife was Episcopal and my mother was Hindu?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If I’m leading my children to be Catholic, why have I not gotten baptized?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do I resolve my liberal beliefs around abortion and homosexuality with the Catechism of the Church?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;god-is-love&quot;&gt;God is Love&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am an unbaptized Catholic.  I’ve had the privilege of having broad exposure to faiths: Catholicism, Protestantism, Hinduism, Buddhism, Judaism, and Islam.  As I strove to understand God, I found Christ’s message of love compelling.  I believe the two greatest commandments are: “You shall love the Lord your God with all your heart, and with all your soul, and with all your mind. . . [and] You shall love your neighbor as yourself” (Catechism of the Catholic Church).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I envision love, I imagine acceptance, protection, and warmth.  As Paul describes,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Love is patient, love is kind.  It does not envy, it does not boast, it is not proud.  It does not dishonor others, it is not self-seeking, it is not easily angered, it keeps no records of wrongs.  Love does not delight in evil but rejoices with the truth.  It always protects, always trusts, always hopes, always perseveres.  Love never fails (Corinthians 12:31 - 13:13).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love is creation, reconciliation, and grace.  Love is a virtue worth cherishing.  A God who loves is balm to the imperfect.  I feel God’s love when I see the awesome, see the holy, see the beautiful, and prey to God; for me it feels like energy goes through me creating a warm buzz in my brain.  I remember first having this experience while attending mass in high school.  I remember associating the feeling with God during a senior retreat called Kairos, a three day student led retreat about self-discovery and developing a personal relationship with God.  At one point in the retreat, we were provided letters from friends and family that we read and shared with others.  I was surprised to receive a letter from my parents; my high school years were tumultuous as my emo self struggled with a feeling of unworthiness that was complicated by untreated depression.  I didn’t think I had earned my parents love.  In the letter, my parents acknowledged the strife we had experienced but reinforced that they were proud of me and loved me.  In that moment, I felt God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last few weeks, I’ve been dealing with a depression flare-up that has encouraged me to face feelings of shame and worthlessness.  At one point, I called my doctor to describe thoughts of suicide and the nurse who answered commended me for being aware that the feelings were irrational.  Love centers me; I know my family, friends, and God loves me.  I’ve learned to trust that love as a flashlight in the darkness and use it to separate reality from what I feel in depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps because of my own struggles, I also understand the value of shared suffering.  In a world of God’s love, we are still far away from heaven on earth.  There is pain; sometimes attributable to free will and at other times, as with childhood cancer, seemingly unexplainable.  To me, the idea that God would choose to experience our suffering in order to model what we should strive for reflects a love that’s observable through sacrifice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;God has honored you. The gospel is the story of how he did it. At the heart of the story is the word servant. Jesus Christ became your servant. . . When Jesus voluntarily became your servant, he lowered himself and elevated you (Shame Interrupted).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we were looking for churches, Missy and I started looking at Episcopal churches.  I noticed some very small differences in the church; probably the most obvious was the focus on the Cross as opposed to the Crucifix.  In philosophy and religious studies in College, I learned to pay attention to these differences.  Differences can help you understand what people have experienced in the past.  For example, the Gospel of Mathew’s focus on lineage contrasts with the Gospel of Luke’s unique parables speak to their respective audiences, Jews and Gentiles.  Whitewashing differences denies individuals their truth, limits our ability to empathize, and prevents our ability to seek justice.  We all have a past.  While our past doesn’t control our future, it does need to be recognized.  Similarly, the focus on the Cross verse Crucifix reflects a theological focus on the resurrection or the passion.  Acceptance of suffering is an important message for me; significant enough that I had a strong preference for the Catholic Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;unbaptized-catholic&quot;&gt;unbaptized catholic&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if I’m an unapologetic Catholic, why don’t I get baptized?  To be honest, I’m looking forward to re-evaluating this decision in counseling.  In the past, I’ve decided not to get baptized because my mom would prefer if I didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my mom first found out I was thinking about converting, she took to me India to learn more about Hinduism.  I learned the core Hindu values are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brahman - The One God.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Atman - God’s expression of creation that exists in individuals.  There is God in all of us.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dharma - The essence of God that makes an individual.  By honoring our essence, we can become one with God.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Karma - A connective experience that unites all of our individual lives and gives us the ability to reunite with the One God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I envision the God of Hinduism as a loving light.  Through love, light creates.  Creation retains a portion of the One God’s light that can be realized when the individual lives in a way that is consistent with God’s essence.  Upon death, the individual rejoins God unless something they experienced in their current life blocks them.  In the event they are blocked, they are shown mercy and given an opportunity to try again in a new life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As my mom pointed out to me, that core belief structure is compatible with following Jesus Christ as a Guru.  In fact, there was a portrait of Jesus in the Hare Krishna Hare Rama temple that Missy and I got married in (for those keeping track Missy and I have been married four times).  Several of my family members have a portrait of Jesus on their personal altars.  It’s a type of whitewashing that acknowledges the message of love Jesus preached while ignoring his Jewish heritage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve grown older my mom’s objections to conversion have varied; but ultimately it boils down to she’s concerned about the judgement of our family and her community.  To date, I have chosen to honor my mother wishes.  I have participated in the church by attending weekly without receiving sacraments.  In this way, I am trying to model behavior for my children as they grow up in the church.  One day, I’ll likely get baptized and join my family fully in the church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;cafeteria-catholic&quot;&gt;cafeteria catholic&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December 2020, I reached out to friends on Facebook because I was struggling with the news that the United States Conference of Catholic Bishops was considering denying Joe Biden communion on the basis of his pro-choice position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abortion is a serious decision that is often made in imperfect situations where there isn’t a good option.  I had a friend who found she was pregnant six months into a relationship with an older man.  She wasn’t ready to be a mother and their relationship wasn’t stable enough to raise a child.  After discussing the pregnancy with her partner, she decided to get an abortion.  I saw the way that decision impacted her and the pain she went through during the procedure.  It wasn’t easy.  I’m glad that I didn’t have to face that decision.  I supported my friend the best I could by being present and not judging her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly one out of three single mothers in the United States live in poverty.  It’s not easy; as a society we don’t provide access to affordable child care and many jobs don’t provide the flexibility single mothers need.  We can do better and if we did I’m convinced abortions would decrease.  In fact, I think aid programs explain the correlation between Democratic presidents and the decrease in abortion rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Catholic church is clear that abortion is evil.  My experience with abortion reflects that, abortion hurts everyone involved and should not be celebrated.  As with most impossible decisions, I think the decision should be made by the people directly involved.  The church states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A person who procures a completed abortion incurs excommunication latae sententiae, by the very commission of the offense . . . The moment a positive law deprives a category of human beings of the protection which civil legislation ought to accord them, the state is denying the equality of all before the law. When the state does not place its power at the service of the rights of each citizen, and in particular of the more vulnerable, the very foundations of a state based on law are undermined (Catechism of the Catholic Church).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same token, the church provides for legitimate defense:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The legitimate defense of persons and societies is not an exception to the prohibition against the murder of the innocent that constitutes intentional killing. “The act of self-defense can have a double effect: the preservation of one’s own life; and the killing of the aggressor. The one is intended, the other is not.”  Love toward oneself remains a fundamental principle of morality. Therefore it is legitimate to insist on respect for one’s own right to life (Catechism of the Catholic Church).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further even grave sins can be forgiven:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Certain particularly grave sins incur excommunication, the most severe ecclesiastical penalty, which impedes the reception of the sacraments and the exercise of certain ecclesiastical acts, and for which absolution consequently cannot be granted, according to canon law, except by the Pope, the bishop of the place or priests authorized by them (Catechism of the Catholic Church).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides abortion, I struggle with the churches teachings on homosexuality.  I find the call for abstinence unrealistic and inappropriate.  I take solace that church also says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The number of men and women who have deep-seated homosexual tendencies is not negligible. This inclination, which is objectively disordered, constitutes for most of them a trial. They must be accepted with respect, compassion, and sensitivity. Every sign of unjust discrimination in their regard should be avoided. These persons are called to fulfill God’s will in their lives and, if they are Christians, to unite to the sacrifice of the Lord’s Cross the difficulties they may encounter from their condition (Catechism of the Catholic Church).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My eight grade religious teacher was gay.  I’m grateful for him.  Two lessons stood out to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He related a story from his grandmother who asked him when he had cut himself, “what color is your blood?”  When he answered red, his grandmother reminded him that regardless of difference everyone’s blood is red.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He pointed out to the class that homosexuality maybe viewed as a sin but so was birth control and masturbation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the Church’s teachings identify that I’m in a sinful relationship with my wife because I’ve had vasectomy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“every action which, whether in anticipation of the conjugal act, or in its accomplishment, or in the development of its natural consequences, proposes, whether as an end or as a means, to render procreation impossible” is intrinsically evil (Catechism of the Catholic Church).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I struggle with the teachings, I pray for discernment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to understand if the focus on abortion and homosexuality is misplaced in the context of Christ’s teachings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to understand if, like Judas, I’m trying to exert my will over God’s will.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you join a community based on values, you don’t get to opt out of values that you struggle with.  I recognize that the decision making power on church teachings rest with the clergy.  At the same time, even a piece criticizing Cardinal Marx for calling for the Catechism’s teaching on homosexuality to be changed recognized:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Catechism isn’t above question or critique, but such inquiries should challenge not what the Catechism teaches but, rather, how it teaches it. The Catechism is, after all, for catechesis, and as such it can fall short in conveying what the Church has established, but this does not affect the holy tradition of truth behind it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think of Jesus going to prostitutes, going to lepers, and going to adulterers.  I find it hard to believe that Jesus would shun people for these violations of the Ten Commandments.  As the catechism says, “it is in the New Covenant in Jesus Christ that their [The Ten Commandments] full meaning would be revealed” (Catechism of the Catholic Church).  Ultimately, I think it’s up to the sinner to resolve his or her sin with God through reconciliation.  Regardless, sin does not grant me the power to judge others.  Likewise, sin does not give me the power to deny others love; one cannot be too stingy with love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-stay&quot;&gt;why stay&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think as the Church’s sex abuse crisis has shown, the Church is not without sin.  We are all doing our best to live a Good Life that was modeled by Jesus Christ.  In 2022, there’s a great deal of sorting that serves to isolate ourselves from diverse perspectives.  Rather than respectfully engaging with people we disagree with, we quit.  I think it’s a tragedy that weaponizes our differences.  It’s certainly not in alignment with the vision of the church as a field hospital for sinners.  I think the struggle with these issues, like a knife grinding on a whetstone, can make the community and individuals better.  I’m confident that the church’s teachings have made me a better person, a better father, and a better husband.  In addition, as a member of the church if I can help someone feel welcome, who otherwise would feel threatened out of place, then I feel like I’m doing God’s work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="faith" /><category term="parenting" /><summary type="html">In Communion, I talk about my faith journey. Specifically I try to answer: +Why I chose Catholicism when my wife was Episcopal and my mother was Hindu? +If I&apos;m leading my children to be Catholic, why have I not gotten baptized? +How do I resolve my liberal beliefs around abortion and homosexuality with the Catechism of the Church?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Armor</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/legacy/Armor/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Armor" /><published>2022-04-11T20:15:59-05:00</published><updated>2022-04-11T20:15:59-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/legacy/Armor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/legacy/Armor/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve started counseling to explore the bittersweet of my soul that surfaces in depression.  It’s my hope through reflection that I’m able to make space with sadness; to make depression less of a thing that I keep locked away until it breaks it’s cage and more of an aspect of personality that I live with and manage.  To that end, I gave my counselor three goals that I wanted to work on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to explore the armor I put around health issues because I think it can prevent me from empathizing with people in pain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to reflect on my need to belong and the boundaries I’ve established in creating my tribe, my family, my work, and my spirituality.  While I think I’m mainly balanced, I think it’s helpful to have check-up because unhealthy behavior is amazingly easy to rationalize away.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to explore the shame I carry for things that I’ve done in my past.  I want to understand the source, any feeding behaviors I may have, and the impact that carrying weight may have on decision making.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the first counseling session, I agreed to reflect more on the issues I have with health issues; I agreed to identify underlying causes and consider what if anything I would be willing to change in my behavior.  So while this post is primarily targeted at that discovery, I think it’ll be useful if I setup some context about me before we dive in together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;background&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My core values are heart and integrity.  For me living with a whole heart means that I give everything I have and more to situations that I find myself in.  Integrity balances my leave-it-on-the-field drive by encouraging self-awareness, candor, and a growth-mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a doer.  If you were to drop me in the middle of the wilderness, I would start walking in a uniform direction because the probability that I’d find a road is high.  I’d try to learn about my surroundings to determine what I would need to do make it back to civilization and start executing on that plan.  In addition to ambiguous situations, I’ll work through almost anything that’s difficult; when the going get’s tough, I get going.  For example, after my wife and I got married, I insisted that we do Sunday night dinners with my parents.  After my dad decided not to attend our wedding, I knew that those dinners would be difficult and there would be many years ahead of repairing the relationship between the family I was creating and my parents.  Nevertheless, I was determined to do my part by showing up.  Having lived with unmedicated depression for nearly thirty years; I think I became a doer because if I stayed still when I was in trouble, I would have drowned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rely on feedback systems to ensure that my effort is well-invested and my effort results in outcomes I associate with living a good life.  Every month I track my weight, sleep, activity, church attendance, dates and other kpi’s.  When I don’t feel satisfied, I try to reflect on proximate causes and things I can do to improve.  I talk to my tribe about difficulty I’m going through.  I read voraciously to learn about new ideas.  As a result, I don’t just do; I get better.  I continually try to become the person I want to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fpr most of my life, I couldn’t imagine that people would deal with adversity in other ways.  When Yammer got acquired by Microsoft, my doer drive was in full swing.  I quickly learned the territory I was going to be responsible for, determined an initial travel schedule, and made contact with teams that I’d support.  In contrast, several of my peers waited for clarification about the role and suggested initiatives before engaging.  Trying to understand the difference, I talked to a mentor who reminded me that sometimes people respond to uncertainty by searching for more information.  We talked about the reasons why that’s an appropriate response: with more information you gain confidence in your direction, with more information you can coordinate your actions with others, and with more information you can leverage the sponsorship of others to move faster.  While the approach was foreign, it was a revelation because I could empathize with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in my career I’d partner with a client executive who would push this concept with me further.  He pointed out that activity doesn’t always generate results; in fact, results correlated when clients could articulate the value of the activity.  He showed me that timing mattered and that sometimes it was best to move at the same speed as the client you were working with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a doer but I also recognize that it’s important to move at the speed of those that I’m working with.  Now, I am being challenged to apply this professional lesson to my personal life in order to better empathize with people who are in pain.  It’s probably not a surprise that I deal with pain by “shaking it off”.  I tend to respond to others in pain with the same type of guidance.  Unfortunately, that’s one of least effective ways to respond to pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;responding-to-pain&quot;&gt;responding to pain&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The human soul doesn’t want to be advised or fixed or saved.  It simply wants to be witnessed, exactly as it is.  Parker Palmer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a video, Megan Devine explains how acknowledgement is the best way to help those suffering; to sit with others who are in pain and not try to fix it.  People are resilient, they’ll find their own path forward.  Acknowledging where they are helps them feel validated and supported.  For me the line between acknowledgement and acceptance is blurry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my youth, my dad didn’t draw lines between punishment, anger, and love.  As a result, I felt that love was conditional.  That was reinforced by what I saw with my parents relationship.  While they never actually divorced, they came close several times.  Most often the fights were about money and I internalized them as: I will love you if you can reduce your wasteful spending.  One time it got so bad, I actually helped my mom put a down-payment on an apartment.  After each argument, my parents reconciled in private which appeared to me as acceptance of the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mom was born with CMT4; she didn’t start walking until she was five.  She’s on several heart medications to manage a weak heart beat.  She has a bulging eye that’s impacted her vision.  While my parents’ arguments were about money, I always felt like health wasn’t far away.  The spending my dad would complain about included spending on medication and massages to manage pain.  I learned that love could be contingent on a persons ability to deal with pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my first committed relationship, I dated a person who lived with Crohn’s disease.  She was in severe pain and struggled.  Over the course of two years, she had her intestines re-sectioned four times ultimately culminating colectomy.  It was painful watching someone I care about, someone who had dreams, lose herself to the pain associated with disease.  I stayed in that relationship too long, in the end sacrificing my undergraduate experience.  As it became clear that she was becoming ill, I tried to accelerate my study so that I could take on the role of the bread-winner.  I ended graduating before I was 20 and ran up an impressive amount of debt trying to make the failed relationship work.  As I saw her fail, I tried to setup a series of positive incentives to encourage her to figure out how to manage her disease.  I even agreed to get married if we could make our lives financially sustainable.  I was trying to setup conditions for my love that could manipulate how my then fiance managed pain.  I wanted her to take control of her life on my timetable; in exchange I would love her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When that relationship ended, I was sad because I felt like I had failed; but I was confident that the relationship had on a whole made me a worse person.  I had learned how to survive and had some great memories but I wasn’t progressing towards a good life.  I determined that I had tried to take responsibility for another person’s choices and thus had setup a relationship based on a house of cards.  In the future, I vowed to only enter relationships on mutual respect; as a partnership of equals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;shutting-down&quot;&gt;shutting down&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my engagement with Missy, she had multiple minor surgeries for what was diagnosed as a Bartholin cyst.  While she was going through that, I couldn’t help but see a similarity to my previous experience with Crohn’s.  I distinctly remember at one point talking to Missy’s brother after she had been admitted to the hospital; I told him I wasn’t sure if I go through another relationship affected by Crohn’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I determined then, as now, that Missy’s support makes me a better person.  She encourages me to do difficult things and she has faith that together we can tackle any challenge.  Her steadiness helps anchor me and provides a base for me to relate with others.  She makes me better; I wasn’t going to give that up for Crohn’s.  At the same token, I was committed to not make the same mistakes that I made in my previous relationship.  Through couple’s counseling I learned how to voice disagreements, define boundaries, and practice unconditional love.  I learned that I could love and support Missy without taking ownership of her problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One boundary I quickly established was around health.  I’d support her and be present when she needed to have a procedure; but I wouldn’t sacrifice my future.  She accepted the limits of support I could provide and she developed her own support network of family and friends that would help her through medical crisis.  In fact, shortly after I got a job offer from Microsoft, Missy was formally diagnosed with Crohn’s and required a major surgery.  As timing would have it, I moved to Minnesota weeks before her surgery.  Through the support of her parents, she got through the surgery and recovered and was able to join me three months later.  In order to protect myself, I would love and support her but I wouldn’t sacrifice experiences for her health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our marriage continued, the boundary worked for us in a large part because her parents are incredibly supportive and could fill this gap that I couldn’t.  Over time, Missy pointed out boundary creep - not only did I not sacrifice but I also was cold to her when she complained about pain.  I would tell her that she needed to figure it out and manage her health.  Eventually she did, becoming an amazing example of what a self-advocating patient looks like.  At the same time, it turned out that the boundary I established around health applied not just to Missy but everyone in my life including our children.  I’m definitely not the parent that will bring you soup in bed when you are sick.  I find that I have some distance with those that I love because I don’t empathize with their suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;going-forward&quot;&gt;going forward&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to close that distance.  I want to support those that I care about.  “The real barrier  . . . is our armor - the thoughts, emotions and behaviors that we use to protect ourselves when we aren’t willing and able to rumble with vulnerability,” Brene Brown says in Daring Leadership.  She continues, “When we stop caring about what anyone thinks, we’re too armored for authentic connection.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Brown also provides an approach for moving forward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rather than protecting and hiding our heart behind bulletproof glass, wholeheartedness is about integration, It’s integrating our thinking, feeling, and behavior.  It’s putting down the armor and bringing forth all of the scraggly, misshapen pieces of our history and folding in all of the different roles that, when falsely separated, keep us feeling exhausted and torn, to make a complex, messy, awesome whole person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me this blog, is an attempt to integrate the compartments of myself.  I’m trying to undergo sense-making of the things I’m passionate about to better understand who I am and inform how I want to live in the future.  In her book, Dr. Brown provides sixteen examples of armor and provides some suggestions on how to put down armor.  Several things flag up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Numbing - the act of leveraging an activity or an addiction to take the edge off pain.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Counter: Sent boundaries and Finding Real Comfort - Broadly defining boundaries is making clear what’s okay and what’s not okay, and why.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hiding Behind Cynicism - expressing frustration through passive-aggressiveness and sarcasm.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Counter: Modeling Clarity, Kindness, and Hope - Say what you mean and mean what you say.  Have a goal, a path. and confidence that it can be achieved.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using Criticism as Protection - Criticism shifts the spotlight off us and onto someone or something else.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Counter: Make Contributions and Take Risks - Come with a point of view and be prepared ot share it.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zigzagging and Avoiding - Zigzagging is a metaphor for trying to dodge the bullets of vulnerability
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Counter: Talking Straight and Taking Action - Bring clarity and awareness to what we’re trying to avoid - then get clear about what needs to be done.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to be able to establish clearer boundaries between acknowledgement and acceptance.  One way I can establish the boundaries is by changing how I react; rather than trying to solve a problem I can be better about responding with curiosity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It sounds like you are dealing with pain, do you want to talk about it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you have a plan to make your situation better?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How can I best support you?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can also set boundaries around how other peoples processes affect me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I understand your suffering right now, but I need a plan.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am going to act because I think it will make the situation better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if this path will lead to success; I do think it’s an attempt to be better.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="heart" /><category term="integrity" /><category term="legacy" /><summary type="html">I work through a mental block that I have around empathizing with other&apos;s illness. I talk about how my personality, and my past contribute to that block and I discuss hopes I have for changing my behavior in the future.</summary></entry></feed>