<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-10-16T21:11:03-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">avisuj</title><subtitle>Avi Sujeeth&apos;s personal blog. This blog captures my adventures  trying to guide my family through the 21st century. It&apos;s my hope  that it&apos;ll help me lead an intentional life and one day provide some  inspiration for my children&apos;s adventures.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Identity, Values, and the Choices We Make</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/parenting/Identity-Values-And-The-Choices-We-Make/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Identity, Values, and the Choices We Make" /><published>2023-08-13T01:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-08-13T01:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/parenting/Identity-Values-And-The-Choices-We-Make</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/parenting/Identity-Values-And-The-Choices-We-Make/">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/697782017619644/posts/1384069062324266/?__cft__[0]=AZVS3j0VgZ0lVby1067q1jloX9EhyPKaYwDtB8lfY0xsUg8zCaIbjRPlGo6PNy4DjSm15WEksvYWES_NnH6QBB7oyfAckkGlsOmMnj79fg0mebWhO7KkxMLgdmHx8TbiaLlf-cqJXkvo4ZUPizkQJae9&amp;amp;__tn__=%2CO%2CP-R&quot;&gt;Philosophy Club&lt;/a&gt;, Nikola recently asked “Why do people compete with each other instead of helping each other?”  This reminded me of a question posed by Daniel Pink in the Power of Regret, why do people make different moral judgments?  Pink provides several examples: “for example, is it wrong for children to talk back to their parents?  To call adults by their first name? Is it wrong for a woman to get an abortion, for a man to marry another man, or for people of any gender to wed multiple spouses?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many times when we’re faced with these differences, we tend to absolutes - I am right and they are wrong.  Instead, what if the different opinions stem from different world views?  The Moral Foundations theory by Jonathan Haidt posits that belief on morality rests on five pillars:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Harm/Care: We should prevent harm and promote care for others.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fairness/Reciprocity: We should be treat people fairly and justly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ingroup/Loyalty: We should value and protect our own social groups.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Authority/Respect: We should value structures that maintain stability and social order.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Purity/Sanctity: We should strive for sacredness, cleanliness, and maintaining a sense of moral purity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These five moral foundations are not universally valued to the same extent across cultures and individuals. Different people and societies may emphasize some foundations more than others, leading to variations in moral values and political beliefs.  An individual’s sense of identity can be shaped by the foundations they prioritize, and their interactions with others who share similar or differing moral foundations can further strengthen or challenge their identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personal identity refers to the distinct set of characteristics, qualities, beliefs, values, interests, and experiences that define an individual as a unique person. It is the core sense of self that distinguishes one person from another.&lt;br /&gt;
Identity is not static; it can evolve over time due to personal experiences, interactions with others, and changes in circumstances.  Over time, individuals may engage in introspection and exploration to better understand themselves. This ongoing process contributes to the development of personal identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Dare to Lead, Brene Brown challenges people to define identity by core values: 
Our values should be so crystallized in our minds, so infallible, so precise and clear and unassailable, that they don’t feel like a choice—they are simply a definition of who we are in our lives. In those hard moments, we know that we are going to pick what’s right, right now, over what is easy. Because that is integrity—choosing courage over comfort; it’s choosing what’s right over what’s fun, fast, or easy; and it’s practicing your values, not just professing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My core values are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/my-core-values-integrity-heart-avi-sujeeth/&quot;&gt;heart and integrity&lt;/a&gt;.  I’ve built a reinforcing sense of identity around.  It helps me be true to myself.  I am:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Catholic - Catholics are called to love God and love one another.  Catholics are encouraged to live with honesty and integrity in all aspects of their lives.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Father and Husband - I love my family and strive to live the Good Life with them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Technologist - I believe building technology can make the world better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People often have agency over certain aspects of their identity, such as their personal beliefs, interests, and values. They can make choices about the ideologies they embrace, the hobbies they pursue, and the values they prioritize.   When making that choice, I think it’s important to build a strong identity.  A strong identity and a weak identity refer to the level of clarity, confidence, and coherence an individual has in their sense of self and affiliations.  A strong identity guides individuals in making decisions that align with their values and aspirations.  People with a weak identity may compare themselves to others more often and feel envious of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My identity helps me live my values and provides a foundation for growth.  I can always be better at living with heart and integrity.  Because these values are things I strive for verse fixed traits; feedback represents an opportunity to learn and enrich my life’s journey.  In fact, I think this provides the foundation to overcome adversity like my recent layoff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, identity, values, and ethics are all intertwined.  When they are reinforcing, they can provide clarity and coherence that provides confidence that we will do what’s right over what is easy.  A well-chosen identity can connect us with others through a shared sense of right and wrong.  Those relationships can provide the energy to go far; further than we could ever go by ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="integrity" /><category term="heart" /><category term="parenting" /><summary type="html">I explore the intriguing question of why people hold differing moral judgments. Drawing inspiration from Daniel Pink&apos;s observations, I delve into the diversity of moral values and the role of personal identity. Through the lens of the Moral Foundations theory and insights from Brene Brown, I examine how conscious cultivation of core values can strengthen identity, guide ethical decisions, and offer a resilient foundation in overcoming life&apos;s challenges.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Journey of Faith and Community</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/faith/a-journey-of-faith-and-community/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Journey of Faith and Community" /><published>2023-08-13T01:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-08-13T01:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/faith/a-journey-of-faith-and-community</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/faith/a-journey-of-faith-and-community/">&lt;p&gt;As I stand at the threshold of the Rite of Acceptance with the Catholic Church, I find myself reflecting on the profound questions that have been posed to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do you see yourself taking up the cross of Christ in your Life?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How has the Word of God come alive for you as you have traveled on your faith journey?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having attended a Marianist high school and Jesuit college, I grew up around the Church.  In high school I struggled mightily with depression.  While my history means I’m predisposed to depression, I also struggled being an immigrant and defining my identity.  I was an &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.avisuj.com/heart/integrity/legacy/Other/&quot;&gt;other&lt;/a&gt; and my otherness fueled the depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first times I felt God’s love was in Chaminade’s senior retreat, Kairos: The Kairos Retreat experience is a special time to reflect on who you are and who you want to be.  During the retreat, we explored what it means to be loved by God and how God’s love reflected in our community.  A letter from my Dad was particularly touching - it acknowledged the strife I was feeling and was steadfast in support.  I realized that I could build my life on the bedrock of God’s love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first times I felt community was when I joined St. Louis University youth group to visit with Pope John Paul II.  The experience was amazing and not what I was expecting.  Students from across the greater Saint Louis area gathered to hear the Pope in a hockey arena.  It was packed.  The sound track could have streamed from K-Love.  The joy was palpable - there was no doubt that the Holy Spirit was among us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of my history and experiences, I contemplate the path of taking up the cross of Christ. It beckons me to deepen my relationship with Him and to embrace my challenges as pathways to growth. The Rite of Catholic Initiation for Adults has shown me that the Word, Worship, and Witness are intended to be communal.  The heart of the church’s teaching is that relationship, captured in the trinity, extends to all of us.  In exploring with others, I am learning things about the church’s teachings.  One enlightening conversation revolved around our individual draws to the Church. I shared my belief, captured in &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.avisuj.com/faith/parenting/Communion/&quot;&gt;Communion&lt;/a&gt;, that the church makes me a better person, a better father, and a better husband.  I pointed out that those teachings have had the benefit of millennia of learnings and tradition.  My friend interjected - don’t forgot about divine inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I embark on this journey, I am confronted with my personal challenge of discerning divine inspiration and staying faithful. What do I seek from God’s Church? The answer resonates clearly: FAITH. It’s through faith that I am empowered to navigate the complexities of life, carrying with me the lessons of the cross, the teachings of the Church, and the everlasting presence of divine inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="faith" /><summary type="html">In my journey towards the Rite of Acceptance with the Catholic Church, I reflect on how taking up the cross of Christ and embracing His teachings has shaped my life. Moments like a transformative retreat experience and a surprising encounter with Pope John Paul II highlighted the power of God&apos;s love and the unity of the Catholic community. As I delve deeper into my faith, I grapple with the call to carry the cross, embrace communal teachings, and discern divine inspiration, finding solace and strength in the enduring embrace of faith.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Embracing Change and Defining Value: My Journey Through a Pending Layoff</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/parenting/My-Journey-Through-a-Pending-Layoff/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embracing Change and Defining Value: My Journey Through a Pending Layoff" /><published>2023-08-04T01:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-08-04T01:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/parenting/My-Journey-Through-a-Pending-Layoff</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/parenting/My-Journey-Through-a-Pending-Layoff/">&lt;p&gt;While I was on vacation, my network started discussing a pending reorganization at Microsoft.  It quickly became clear that my role was likely to be impacted.  On July 10th, my skip manager asked me to join a team call with HR to officially deliver the news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bad things sometimes happen to good people.  I think a person’s character is defined by how they react - how they get back up and learn from past experiences.  I wanted to illustrate to the kids: that a person’s value is not defined by their job, that it’s important to be present with people, and that resilience happens by executing plans with the end in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin, a person’s value is not defined by their job.  While it’s common knowledge, I think it can be harder to realize because salary and rewards are some of the most visible signs of value.   In fact, I think value comes from being human, economic value, leading others, and protecting others &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.avisuj.com/integrity/heart/legacy/parenting/Unpacking-the-Meaning-of-Value-Why-Innate-Worth-Outlasts-Job-Titles/&quot;&gt;Unpacking the Meaning of Value: Why Innate Worth Outlasts Job Titles&lt;/a&gt;.  My life has started to reflect this as I’ve changed my identity from a Microsoft employee to a Catholic, a Father, and a Technologist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because my identity isn’t my job, I’m able to reflect on transferable skills and employment as a way of generating I’m economic value.  In fact, I don’t feel threatened by the lay-off instead I see it for what it is - a bet by company leadership that the job I was doing can be distributed to other employees who are augmented by Artificial Intelligence.  I can even appreciate that Microsoft is trying to live what it sells and I’ll be interested to see if this value proposition for generative artificial intelligence can actually be realized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am still the same person I was before the lay-off.  I still own the relationships I’ve built over the years.  I have unique skills that I leverage to serve others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover it’s important to be present with people.  When we got the news, Missy asked if we should cancel the vacation.  I didn’t think that was a good idea because the vacation is a great opportunity to spend time together as a family.  I will always treasure the fishing memories from the trip and I hope we’ll have more time to explore that past time.  While I did take some time out to stake out job opportunities, I tried to box the time that I would spend so that I could be present with the family on the vacation.  While I’m sure I did better some days than others, being present was always top of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, resilience happens by executing plans with the end in mind.  Having been laid off, I know one of the biggest challenges with being unemployed is the lack of structure.  I’m trying to illustrate through my search how to deconstruct a problem and develop tactics to address it.  Like with exercise, showing up every day is the clearest path to success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Layoffs are an aspect of today’s business world.  My character is defined by how I deal with adversity.  This gives me the opportunity to model behaviors that I hope my kids can embrace.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="integrity" /><category term="heart" /><category term="parenting" /><summary type="html">In my blog post, I reflect on the pending layoff at Microsoft and stress the importance of realizing that my value is not solely tied to my job. I share how I&apos;ve embraced change, explored transferable skills, and maintained resilience during this challenging time. Being present with my family and executing plans with a positive mindset have helped me grow and set an example for my children.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Discovering Purpose: Starting the Sujeeth Foundation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/integrity/legacy/heart/parenting/Discovering-Purpose/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Discovering Purpose: Starting the Sujeeth Foundation" /><published>2023-06-18T01:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-06-18T01:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/integrity/legacy/heart/parenting/Discovering-Purpose</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/integrity/legacy/heart/parenting/Discovering-Purpose/">&lt;p&gt;Starting things is hard.  Over the last month I know the time I’ve been putting into the Sujeeth Foundation has taken away from family.  I hope to share with you why I’m investing in this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sujeeth Foundation is an organization that tries to help students unlock the opportunity of education. Some years ago, we has the fortune to come into some unexpected money.  We were able to award a scholarship which encouraged a friend to get her masters.  Education changed our life - the idea that we can use education to help others change their lives is empowering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve come to believe that economic life has three stages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Early Career - This is the messy process of discovering your interests and identifying your Ikigai.  I navigated this through experimentation, education, growth mindset, and self reflection.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mid Life - This is about marshaling the resources you have built to sustain yourself as you try to preserve time.  As I’ve gotten older, I’ve learned to appreciate time as a finite resource.  This involves growing total assets and generating free cash flow.  The stock market is an excellent vehicle to grow assets.  Business and real estate are great vehicles to increase cash flow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;End Life - This is about establishing a legacy.  For me, I think it will be about how I’m connected with others, the impact I’ve had and how people will remember me.  You die twice - the day you die and the day people no longer remember your name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Sunday at church, I hear a great framework for evaluating works:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good Action: Good action refers to engaging in morally upright and beneficial behaviors. It involves acting in ways that are considered morally right, just, and fair.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good Intention: Good intention refers to the underlying motivation or purpose behind an action. It involves having virtuous motives and a genuine desire to do good. When someone acts with good intention, they are guided by ethical principles, such as empathy, compassion, fairness, and a sense of moral responsibility.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good Consequence: Good consequence refers to the positive outcomes or results that arise from an action. It recognizes that the impact of our actions can have far-reaching effects on others and society. Good consequences are those that promote well-being, create happiness, and contribute to the greater good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had a few concerns around the foundation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is this only about legacy?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is this God’s calling?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is this effective?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you start something you are testing a value population with a community you are trying to serve.  While it seems like it would be easy to award a regular scholarship, some of the other things I’m doing with the foundation are more tenuous.  For example, are students looking for guidance on how to unlock value from education or are they just looking for financial assistance?  From that questions stems a flood of others including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will people choose to apply?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will people order the books I recommend?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will those books make material impact on how people approach life?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will people join Circles?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will people donate or volunteer?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe if I’m truly serving people and making a difference in someone’s life these questions will work themselves out. Originally, I had planned to do the work on the foundation until after I had retired.  Waiting doesn’t answer questions.  Waiting burns time you will never get back.  Waiting reduces your ability to react by delaying your opportunities for learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I prayed about it.  I concluded we had an opportunity to try now.  Through this process, I hope to learn if I’m really able to make an impact.  Maybe I’ll find a better way to drive even more impact.  Regardless, I think what I learn will be valuable in efforts that I’m not even aware of.  In the end, it’s in God’s hands.  I will be open to go where he calls me.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="integrity" /><category term="legacy" /><category term="heart" /><category term="parenting" /><summary type="html">In this blog post, I share the motivations behind the Sujeeth Foundation, which aims to unlock the transformative power of education for students. Reflecting on personal experiences, I highlight the three stages of economic life, emphasizing the importance of self-discovery, resource building, and leaving a meaningful legacy. Guided by an ethical framework of good action, good intention, and good consequence, I embark on this journey to make a positive impact and learn how education can truly change lives.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Dual Nature of Human Thinking: Integrating Intuition and Deliberation for Success</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/parenting/The-Dual-Nature-of-Human-Thinking/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Dual Nature of Human Thinking: Integrating Intuition and Deliberation for Success" /><published>2023-04-14T01:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-04-14T01:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/parenting/The-Dual-Nature-of-Human-Thinking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/parenting/The-Dual-Nature-of-Human-Thinking/">&lt;p&gt;I am currently reading the Art of Possibility by Rosamund Stone Zander, a counselor, and Benjamin Zander, a conductor and teacher.  They talk about two selves: the measuring self and the full self. The measuring self is concerned with how you compare to others and how you measure up to external standards. The full self is concerned with your own internal standards and values.  They provide 12 practices such as “It’s all invented”, “Giving an A”, and “The Way Things Are” that can help you change your perspective in order to see new possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over Easter, I related how Mr. Zander manifested his practice of “Giving an A” at New England Conservatory of Music by literally giving his students an A in exchange for a detailed paper describing what they did to deserve an A - an exercise that forces the students to articulate their internal goals are.  His point is that the measuring self can be limiting.  In a similar way, Carol Dweck describes the concept of mindset and how it affects our lives.  Her book, Mindset, argues that people have either a fixed mindset or a growth mindset. A fixed mindset is one in which people believe that their abilities are fixed and cannot be changed. A growth mindset is one in which people believe that their abilities can be developed through hard work and dedication. The book argues that people with a growth mindset are more likely to succeed in life because they are more willing to take risks and learn from their mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet when I found myself taking about Art of Possibility - I found myself hedging the explanation.  Maybe “Giving an A” only applied when you were dealing with top performers, like musicians studying at the New England Conservatory of Music.  “Giving an A” is about believing the best about the other people you interact with.  When we believe the best about others we open ourselves up to their feedback, that feedback gives us opportunities to learn, learning helps us embrace new possibilities.  Indeed, it’s similar to the idea of rejecting victim stories presented in Thanks for Feedback by Douglas Stone and Sheila Heen.  A victim story makes us out to be innocent sufferers in the predicament while a villain story helps us justify any negative action we take toward the other by attributing evil or malicious motives. In order to receive feedback, we have to realize that they aren’t villains&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like then the concept has broad application.  So why did I hedge?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more I read about human psychology, the more impressed I am with how brain operates in dual modes.  In Thinking Fast and Slow, Daniel Kahneman describes two systems that drive the way we think: System 1 is fast, intuitive, and emotional; System 2 is slower, more deliberative, and more logical.  While both modes have purpose, sometimes we are served in intentionally shifting the mode we are in.  Tying back to the Art of Possibility:  I see the calculating self as deliberative and logical and the full self as intuitive and emotional.  The Art of Possibility then is making the case that to embrace possibility we have to shift our state to System 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that there are times when it makes sense to embrace our intuitive and emotional self.  Yet while I was related the story, I found myself wondering is it really fair to give everyone an A?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fairness, like many amorphous topics, is multifaceted and includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consistency: A decision is considered fair if it is consistent with established rules, norms, and procedures. If a decision is arbitrary or made on the basis of personal biases, it may be considered unfair.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Impartiality: A decision is considered fair if it is made without bias or prejudice towards any particular individual or group. This means that the decision-maker must be neutral and objective, and must not favor one group or individual over another.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transparency: A decision is considered fair if the decision-making process is transparent and open to scrutiny. This means that the decision-maker must be willing to explain their reasoning and provide clear justifications for the decision.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accessibility: A decision is considered fair if it is accessible to all affected parties. This means that all parties must have equal access to information and resources that are relevant to the decision.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consequences: A decision is considered fair if its consequences are distributed fairly and equitably among all affected parties. This means that the decision should not disproportionately benefit or harm any particular individual or group.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Participation: A decision is considered fair if all affected parties have the opportunity to participate in the decision-making process. This means that all parties must have the opportunity to express their views and have their voices heard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Giving an A” is inconsistent with how I understand school triggering my concern.  At the same time, it met every other criteria.  In the end, the process appeared to result in better outcomes for the students in the class.  Sometimes, I think we need to break the rules in order to get out of the box that we are in.  In this scenario, trying to help students to embrace their mastery, “Giving an A” makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reflection, I think:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We work in two ways: fast intuitive and emotional AND slower, deliberative and logical.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When we are trying to explore the unknown, our intuitive and emotional self can help us hear feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When we are trying to improve, our slower deliberative and logical self can help us process feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By integrating both processes and embracing mistakes, we learn.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We should be mindful of how our actions affect others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ultimately hedged because it’s not always right to “Give an A”.  Sometimes it’s important to be able to measure performance to get a picture of the way things are so that you can improve.  Likewise, sometimes it’s important to set that aside so you can break through to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="integrity" /><category term="heart" /><category term="parenting" /><summary type="html">The blog post discusses the concept of &apos;Giving an A&apos; from the book &apos;The Art of Possibility&apos; by Rosamund Stone Zander and Benjamin Zander, and how it relates to the dual modes of thinking in the brain. Embracing both fast, intuitive, and emotional thinking and slower, deliberative, and logical thinking is important for learning and growth.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring the Intersection of AI and Human Values: Opportunities, Challenges, and Ethics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/technology/Exploring-the-Intersection-of-AI-and-Human-Values-Opportunities-Challenges-Ethics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring the Intersection of AI and Human Values: Opportunities, Challenges, and Ethics" /><published>2023-04-08T01:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-04-08T01:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/technology/Exploring-the-Intersection-of-AI-and-Human-Values-Opportunities-Challenges-Ethics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/technology/Exploring-the-Intersection-of-AI-and-Human-Values-Opportunities-Challenges-Ethics/">&lt;p&gt;I’m starting to use ChatGPT to summarize documents, plan my summer vacation, and write blog posts.  It’s been an amazing assistant that I’m going to put to the test as I try to do even more with the same finite time I have available.  It’s given me an intermediary choice between outsourcing an activity and doing it myself; getting automated assistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, this summer we are planning a vacation from Miami to Bar Harbor Maine.  I think I’ll be an amazing experience taking us through ten cities on the east coast - through national parks, museums, cities and landmarks in thirty days.  Initially, Missy and I set target locations and decided on potential dates.  After, I used ChatGPT to generate suggestions about specific itinerary that we should do in each location.  In combination with packaged tours, we were able to get to an itinerary that is tailored to us.  Because we had control, I was able to leverage loyalty programs that we have with Enterprise, Marriott, and Amtrak to maximize our benefits.  Because I value that control, I’ve taken the role of a travel agent for the trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial intelligence (AI) is the ability of machines to perform tasks that normally require human intelligence, such as reasoning, learning, decision making, and creativity. AI has been advancing rapidly in recent years, thanks to the availability of large amounts of data, powerful computing resources, and innovative algorithms. AI has also been applied to various domains and industries, such as health care, education, entertainment, finance, security, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI has brought many benefits and opportunities to humanity, such as improving efficiency, productivity, quality, and innovation. However, AI also poses many challenges and risks, such as ethical dilemmas, social impacts, legal issues, and existential threats. How can we ensure that AI is used for good and not evil? How can we balance the benefits and risks of AI? How can we respect human values and dignity in the age of AI?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently read Moonwalking with Einstein by Joshua Foer.  In the book, Foer recounts how he became interested in memory training and over the course of a year became the US memory champion.  Memory training was once a critical part in education.  As we started relying on writing and later devices to help our memory, memory training became impractical.  Even so, it feels like there was something that was lost:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mere reading is not necessarily learning—a fact that I am personally confronted with every time I try to remember the contents of a book I’ve just put down. To really learn a text, one had to memorize it. As the early-eighteenth-century Dutch poet Jan Luyken put it, “One book, printed in the Heart’s own wax / Is worth a thousand in the stacks.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that’s the case with memory, what happens when you augment the way you think with artificial intelligence?  If all people possess Descartes “good sense”, the ability to distinguish truth from fiction, than do I retain my being as long as I am accountable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think these questions are important because they touch upon the core of what makes us human. As humans, we have a unique capacity to think critically, creatively, and ethically. We have a unique ability to reflect on ourselves and our actions. We have a unique responsibility to act according to our moral values and principles. We have a unique dignity that deserves respect and protection. We have a unique solidarity that binds us together as a community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these human qualities are not fixed or static. They are dynamic and evolving. They are influenced by our environment and our interactions with others. They are also influenced by our tools and technologies. As Marshall McLuhan famously said: “We shape our tools and thereafter our tools shape us.” This means that the technologies we use can affect how we think, feel, and act. They can also affect how we perceive ourselves and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethical artificial intelligence is a topic that concerns how humans and machines interact with each other in a way that respects human values, rights, and dignity. It also involves the moral principles and guidelines that should inform the design, development, and deployment of AI systems, as well as the accountability and responsibility of those who create and use them. Some of the main ethical principles of AI are transparency, fairness, non-maleficence, beneficence, privacy, trust, sustainability, dignity, and solidarity . These principles aim to ensure that AI systems are aligned with human interests and values, and do not cause harm or injustice to individuals or society . Ethical AI is important because it can have significant impacts on various aspects of human life, such as health, education, work, security, and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the potential of the unknown will drive further exploration.  While we are walking the path, we will learn how our creation affects us - if it leads us to harness more knowledge or instead reinforce our vices.  In truth, it will probably do both.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="integrity" /><category term="heart" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html">This blog post explores the intersection of artificial intelligence (AI) and human values, including the benefits and risks of AI, the impact of AI on human qualities and dignity, and the importance of ethical AI. It discusses the potential of AI to augment human capabilities, but also the need to ensure that AI is aligned with human interests and values and does not cause harm or injustice. Ultimately, it highlights the dynamic and evolving nature of human qualities and the role of technology in shaping them, and calls for a responsible and reflective approach to the design, development, and use of AI systems.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Living an Agile Life: Coping with Unknown Unknowns</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/integrity/parenting/Living-an-Agile-Life-Coping-with-Unknown-Unknowns/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Living an Agile Life: Coping with Unknown Unknowns" /><published>2023-04-07T01:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-04-07T01:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/integrity/parenting/Living-an-Agile-Life-Coping-with-Unknown-Unknowns</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/integrity/parenting/Living-an-Agile-Life-Coping-with-Unknown-Unknowns/">&lt;p&gt;On the precipice of the Iraq Invasion, Donald Rumsfeld, the former US Secretary of Defense, said that there are three types of things in the world:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Known knowns: These are things that we know that we know. For example, we know that the Earth is round and that water is wet.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Known unknowns: These are things that we know that we don’t know. For example, we don’t know when the next earthquake will happen or who will win the next election.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unknown unknowns: These are things that we don’t know that we don’t know. These are the most unpredictable and surprising things that can happen. For example, we didn’t know that a pandemic would hit the world in 2020 or that a new variant of the virus would emerge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unknown unknowns are future outcomes, events, circumstances, or consequences that we cannot predict. We cannot plan for them either. We don’t even know when and where to search for them. They pose a potentially greater risk simply because they cannot be anticipated based on past experience or investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I look into the future, it feels like I’m surrounded with unknown unknowns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will the world order hold&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will there be nuclear war&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will artificial intelligence disrupt society&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s ok not to know the future.  In software development, the agile process was created to handle the unknown unknowns. Agile is a method of software development that was created to handle complex and uncertain projects. It’s based on four principles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deliver value early and often: Instead of waiting for a perfect product or solution, agile teams deliver small, testable, and valuable features or ideas in short cycles called sprints. This way, they can get feedback from customers or users and improve their product or solution quickly and continuously.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Embrace change: Instead of resisting or fearing change, agile teams welcome it as an opportunity to learn and grow. They are flexible and responsive to changing requirements, market conditions, customer needs, and feedback. They also experiment with new ideas and technologies to find better ways of doing things.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collaborate: Instead of working in silos or hierarchies, agile teams work together as self-organizing and cross-functional units. They communicate openly and frequently with each other and with their stakeholders. They also share their knowledge, skills, and resources to achieve their common goals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reflect and improve: Instead of repeating the same mistakes or sticking to the same habits, agile teams reflect on their performance and processes regularly. They identify what works well and what needs improvement. They also take action to implement changes and measure their impact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach lets you adjust to changing environment by taking moments to recalibrate the plan from things you’ve learned.  Those micro-adjustments can make a world of difference in achieving a goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that agile is not only a way of developing software but also a way of living life. It can help us cope with unknown unknowns by making us more adaptable, creative, and resilient.  That’s why I have adopted agile as my personal philosophy and practice. I have set some goals for myself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to get into better shape&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to retire in Hawaii&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to see my kids be successful&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to make difference in the world through my work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to start a scholarship to inspire others to live their best lives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have to tackle all the things at once, but I can set goals like how much I need to have saved to retire to Hawaii or start the scholarship fund.  And I can look for opportunities to start things earlier.  For example, I’m investigating what it would take to start awarding a $5K annual scholarship right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By living my life as close to the present as I can, I get to savor simple pleasures, focus on today’s actions, and embrace opportunities as they appear.  Reflecting on how I’ve done monthly, I can ensure that I am connecting what I’m doing with my long term goals.  In addition, I try to periodically look up to determine if I’m still happy with where I think I’m going.  When the world flips on its head, I hope this approach will allow me to adapt to the changes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="integrity" /><category term="parenting" /><summary type="html">This blog post explores the concept of unknown unknowns and how they can impact our lives. It discusses the agile methodology as a way of coping with uncertainties and achieving personal goals. By breaking down goals into smaller tasks, embracing change, collaborating, and reflecting, we can better adapt to unknowns and live our best lives.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unpacking the Meaning of Value: Why Innate Worth Outlasts Job Titles</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/legacy/parenting/Unpacking-the-Meaning-of-Value-Why-Innate-Worth-Outlasts-Job-Titles/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unpacking the Meaning of Value: Why Innate Worth Outlasts Job Titles" /><published>2023-02-18T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-02-18T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/legacy/parenting/Unpacking-the-Meaning-of-Value-Why-Innate-Worth-Outlasts-Job-Titles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/legacy/parenting/Unpacking-the-Meaning-of-Value-Why-Innate-Worth-Outlasts-Job-Titles/">&lt;p&gt;It’s layoff season.  While this round, I’m safe - I’ve been let go twice in my career so far.  The first time I laid off it was jarring for me because I defined my value by my job.  Clearly, I’m more than my job.  I’m also a son, husband, father, community member, volunteer, church goer, gym member, mentor, and friend.  I have many roles.  I’ve come to realize value doesn’t come from a role.  I think value is endowed by our creator - as the declaration of independence says “all men are created equal, that they are endowed by their Creator with certain unalienable rights, that among these are Life, Liberty and the Pursuit of happiness.”  Besides our innate value, I think value is also bestowed by others.  I’ve come to believe that bestowed value is transient while innate value is permanent and real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;sources-of-value&quot;&gt;Sources of Value&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Value is a measure of worth.  It is observable.  I think an individual’s value comes from:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being Human&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Providing Economic Value&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leading Others&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Protecting Others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;innate-value&quot;&gt;Innate Value&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our core value is rooted in our humanity; in our connections, potential, and connectedness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have connections with each other.  Everyone is a son, daughter, mother, or father.  Those connections can be established via blood or through deepened relationships.  Individuals are cherished and that demands respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have untold potential.  Today we stand on the shoulder’s of those who came before us through an arc of history that has seen life expectancy rise, wealth grow, and peace expand.  Moreover, we have control over our destiny - through our choices and our efforts we can change the path we are on.  Never underestimate a fellow human; instead show reverence because one day a human will solve a problem that today is impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are connected with each other through empathy.  Our emotions connect us.  “The sadness from which compassion springs is a pro-social emotion, an agent of connection and love” (Bittersweet).  When you see another person, try to see yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bestowed-value&quot;&gt;Bestowed Value&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other sources of value result from our inter personal interactions.  We ascribe value to those who provide service.  In Leaders Eat Last, Simon Sinek relates that hierarchy was established to promote societal order.  Sinek continues that a leaders value is rooted in their ability to serve the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This premise is echoed through anecdote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every great company starts by solving an important problem. (Startup.com)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The best test as a leader is: Do those served grow as persons; do they become healthier, wiser, freer, more autonomous, more likely themselves to become leaders? (Robert Greenleaf)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being a soldier is more than courage; it’s sacrificing yourself for something greater than yourself. (Anonymous)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We pay, honor, and respect those who provide service.  However, this value is ultimately fleeting.  Rich have become poor.  Politicians have become criminals.  Veterans have become homeless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because bestowed value can lead to inequity, it can be easy to covet.  In warning, Simon Sinek points out that a false leader will struggle to hold on to their position once they’ve got it because the value of leadership comes from the people. “It is nice to be important, but it’s more important to be nice.” (Walter Winchell)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;lasting-value&quot;&gt;Lasting Value&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Power of Positivity, the regrets of people on their deathbed are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Didn’t spend enough time with their family.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wasn’t kind, patient, or loving enough.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Should’ve taken more risks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Didn’t express their feelings to loved ones or themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Didn’t forgive when their was time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we face death, it’s not bestowed value we treasure.  Instead we focus on our innate value and the innate value of those closest to us.  If there’s a lesson here, I think it’s to appreciate each person as God given.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="integrity" /><category term="heart" /><category term="legacy" /><category term="parenting" /><summary type="html">This post explores the true sources of value in human life, distinguishing between innate value, which is rooted in our humanity and connections with others, and bestowed value, which is based on economic or social status. I argue that appreciating and valuing each person as God-given is key to recognizing and honoring our own innate worth and that of others.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Frustrated with My Health; Trying to Trust The Process</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/Frustration-Trust-The-Process/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Frustrated with My Health; Trying to Trust The Process" /><published>2023-01-02T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-01-02T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/Frustration-Trust-The-Process</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/integrity/heart/Frustration-Trust-The-Process/">&lt;p&gt;My post on the new year doesn’t adequately capture the frustration I feel around 2022.  I did the right things but indicators around my health are neutral at best.  Compared to 2021, I was 45% more active.  How is it that you can exercise more yet have many of the signals of your cardio vascular age (hrv, cholesterol, lipids) fall out of control?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, it’s a signal of one of few possibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m working on the wrong things with regards to my health.  In effect, I’m trying to climb the wrong mountain.  As I’m reflecting on my progress, I’m frustrated because I’m not where I thought I’d be.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I haven’t given the process enough time to work.  Progress isn’t linear and it’s easy to get frustrated when results of effort aren’t visible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m working on things poorly.  Bad practice leads to middling results.  Good practice leads to perfection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;working-on-the-wrong-things&quot;&gt;Working on the Wrong Things&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Seven Habits of Highly Effective People, Steven Covey relates a story of two groups of producers who are working they’re we through a jungle.  A leader is the one who climbs a tree, surveys the entire situation, and shouts “Wrong Jungle”.  Managers respond by saying “But, we’re making progress.”  According to Covey, “Effectiveness - often even survival - does not depend solely on how much effort we expand, but on whether or not the effort we spend is in the right jungle.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My health reports should be viewed as signals; understanding what the signals mean is important.  I’m confident they aren’t telling me to exercise less.  According to the American Heart Association, people who exercise at least 150 minutes a week materially reduce their risk of heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, exercise alone may not be enough.  According to (CNET)[https://www.cnet.com/health/fitness/how-to-get-a-six-pack-with-diet-and-exercise/], “No matter how strong your ab muscles are, they’re not going to show through unless you have a low enough body fat.”  Body fat results from eating a calorie surplus - the excess calories get stored as body fat.  The last time I made significant progress at reducing my body fat was when I tracked my meals via MyFitnessPal.  Working from home means I take less steps and I’m surrounded by food.  Even when I’m exerting some self-control, it’s easy for me to unconsciously run a calorie surplus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The message I’m hearing from my health reports is that I need to track what I eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;progress-isnt-linear&quot;&gt;Progress isn’t Linear&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People imagine progress as  a straight line up and to right.  As time marches, you make steady progress towards the goal.  The reality is much of different because the journey to success is full of learning.  What works?  What doesn’t?  In addition, we live in complex systems and things outside of control can have affect.  Are there new stressors?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-theme=&quot;dark&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Progress Isn&amp;#39;t Linear - &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/LqGTXFkp4q&quot;&gt;https://t.co/LqGTXFkp4q&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/sVQOk5IF5r&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/sVQOk5IF5r&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; avisuj (@avisuj) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/avisuj/status/1610054108219678721?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;January 2, 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve learned that instead of measuring progress as achievement to a goal, it’s better to measure learning.  Life is an experiment, if you learn from the shots you take you will eventually make a basket.  Further signal doesn’t always mean insight.  For example, I’m obviously frustrated with my cardiovascular health.  If I took that signal to mean that I should dramatically change my work out - I may creating more damage than benefit.  After all, doing something imperfect consistently is more likely to result in progress than doing the perfect thing occasionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ed Camult shares in Creativity that Pixar has a maxim “Trust the Process”.  While Ed’s talking about the process that Pixar setup for story review, I think can be applied to any process that follows the scientific method.  Learning is the outcome of observing, forming a hypothesis, running an experiment, and submitting for a peer review.  That type of process helps you learn which makes you better at what you pursue over a long enough time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I haven’t been at this long enough.  In fact, after I’ve made the changes to my diet I found that my HRV scores recently have doubled!  Implementing small changes from learnings can result in progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;bad-practice&quot;&gt;Bad Practice&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Peak, Anders Erickson relates a story of how we learn.  When we want to learn a new skill like Tennis, we practice until it becomes automatic.  While we still have weaknesses, we stop improving because we aren’t deliberate.  We’re practicing things we’re good at rather than what our weaknesses are.  To overcome this obstacle, Erickson states it’s important to have well defined goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I certainly am not a professional weight lifter or cyclist.  It very well could be that I’m not seeing health improvements because I’m not doing the right activities.  For example, my cycling time hasn’t materially improved over the last year.  Likewise, I’m lifting a bit less weight than I used to lift two years ago.  I probably could get better outcomes if I saw a personal trainer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal isn’t to be professional cyclist or lifter.  Instead, I want to increase my health span and do more of what I enjoy.  To that end, I am partnering with a physician who specialized in precision health.  I think they’ll be able to help me understand if it would be worthwhile to invest in a trainer or if a different experiment is more promising.  My first appointment is February 6th.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="integrity" /><category term="heart" /><summary type="html">My post on the new year doesn&apos;t adequately capture the frustration I feel around 2022. I did the right things but indicators around my health are neutral at best. Compared to 2021, I was 45% more active. How is it that you can exercise more yet have many of the signals of your cardio vascular age (hrv, cholesterol, lipids) fall out of control?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Looking Back at 2022: Year in Review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/integrity/investing/legacy/tech/Looking-Back-at-2022-Year-in-Review/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Looking Back at 2022: Year in Review" /><published>2022-12-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-12-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/integrity/investing/legacy/tech/Looking-Back-at-2022-Year-in-Review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/integrity/investing/legacy/tech/Looking-Back-at-2022-Year-in-Review/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t do 2022 differently, but there are definitely some changes I want to take into 2023.  Over the year, we made some great memories.  Financially, we were even with the market.  Given the market stress and significant one time expenses, I’m impressed with how our new budgeting system is working.  I wish we would have adopted it sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professionally, I couldn’t be happier with the job move into Patient experience.  I’m hopeful that the work I’ve put in will become visible through customer success communicated via case studies shortly.  I feel like I’m making a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going forward to 2023, I’m going to watch what I eat more carefully.  In addition, we need to be more accountable to our travel budget.  This year was ok, I hope next year is even better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;notable-events&quot;&gt;Notable Events&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;European Vacation - This year we went on amazing vacation through central Europe.  We were able to cross ten cities and eleven countries by train.  Notable memories include: a gondola in Venice, an opera in Prague, and the Ann Frank House.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thanksgiving Vacation - We visited the Grand Canyon with Missy’s parents.  It was the first time the kids got to see the Grand Canyon.  Afterwards, we spent a few days in Huntington Beach by the Ocean.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Passing of Todd Fujawa - Todd’s a friend.  His daughter and Abby are friends.  His sudden passing was a surprise that hit too close to home.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Death of Hedwig - Missy totaled our Chrysler Pacifica and we ended up purchasing another one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;wellness&quot;&gt;Wellness&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the year, I’ve gained 12 pounds while I’ve lost 2” around my waist.  I was 25% more active than last year contributing to increased muscle mass.  At the same token, I’m approaching my 2018 weight.  My health markers reflect it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My cholesterol and lipid levels are as high as 2018.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My resting heart beat has increased three beats per minute.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My fitness level score decreased by two points.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 2023, I need to get my weight under control.  As such, I’m restarting logging my food.  If I want to eat it, I need to log it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;finances&quot;&gt;Finances&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year the bubble burst.  In addition, we spent $74K more than last year.  In total, we lost 15% of our net worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our top three spending categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$54K Automotive - replacing a car&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$43K Taxes - underpayment on last year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$38K Travel - $13K over budget&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ignoring the above spending categories, expenses were within expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s also important to view 2022 in context of the broader market.  The benchmarks of SPY and CoinGecko were down 20% and 62% respectively.  Broadly, our investments asset classes performed at par with benchmarks.  As a result of the bear market, our investments have been concentrated in stock equities.  In addition passive income is only slightly growing.  Getting to a balanced ratio is going to take intentional saving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A notable success is that our credit card balances were low throughout the year.  The new budgeting system I’ve put in place that forecasts episodic expenses and saves for them via dedicated accounts has proven to be remarkably successful.  I think prepaying our expenses is the heart of “pay yourself first” and really helped improve our resiliency throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;sustainability&quot;&gt;Sustainability&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our electricity usage was flat at 21,500 kWh.  Excluding AC, the largest consumers were dehumidifier, car, and garage fan.  Going forward, we’re going to use the dehumidifier and garage fan less.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our natural gas usage was flat at 390 CCF.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="integrity" /><category term="investing" /><category term="legacy" /><category term="tech" /><summary type="html">I wouldn&apos;t do 2022 differently, but there are definitely some changes I want to take into 2023. Over the year, we made some great memories. Financially, we were even with the market. Given the market stress and significant one time expenses, I&apos;m impressed with how our new budgeting system is working. I wish we would have adopted it sooner.</summary></entry></feed>