<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-12-18T09:57:29-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">avisuj</title><subtitle>Avi Sujeeth's personal blog. This blog captures my adventures  trying to guide my family through the 21st century. It's my hope  that it'll help me lead an intentional life and one day provide some  inspiration for my children's adventures.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">On Death and Dying</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/faith/heart/On-Death-and-Dying/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Death and Dying" /><published>2022-11-21T16:57:59-06:00</published><updated>2022-11-21T16:57:59-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/faith/heart/On-Death-and-Dying</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/faith/heart/On-Death-and-Dying/">&lt;p&gt;As I lit our gas fireplace last night, the flames seemed to dance.  But just as quickly as they came alive, they would snuff out as the fuel exhausted.  Dead.  I think this impermanence lends to the flames beauty.  Demands attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend of the family passed away last night.  He left behind his wife, two daughters (20 and 12) and a son (9).  His middle child and Abby are friends.  Dead.  Sometimes life isn’t fair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully in my last episode of depression, I went deep on grief:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Its-That-Youre-Not-Understand-ebook/dp/B073XXYKLP/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=it%27s+ok+that+you%27re+not+ok&amp;amp;qid=1669070005&amp;amp;s=digital-text&amp;amp;sprefix=it%27s+ok+%2Cdigital-text%2C204&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot;&gt;It’s OK that You’re NOT OK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Sanctuary-Memoir-Emily-Rapp-Black-ebook/dp/B087BCBNWW/ref=sr_1_1?crid=18Z9SZIEPT2RC&amp;amp;keywords=sanctuary+a+memoir&amp;amp;qid=1669070037&amp;amp;s=digital-text&amp;amp;sprefix=sanctuary+a+memoir%2Cdigital-text%2C164&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot;&gt;Sanctuary: a Memoir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Shame-Interrupted-Lifts-Worthlessness-Rejection-ebook/dp/B007WWB990/ref=sr_1_1?crid=YFO9OGB5KQ9A&amp;amp;keywords=shame+interrupted&amp;amp;qid=1669070061&amp;amp;s=digital-text&amp;amp;sprefix=shame+interrupted%2Cdigital-text%2C160&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot;&gt;Shame Interrupted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I watched &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l2zLCCRT-nE&quot;&gt;Refuge in Grief&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Bittersweet-Sorrow-Longing-Make-Whole/dp/B09BW27GLR/ref=sr_1_1?crid=12PVST2871E1S&amp;amp;keywords=bittersweet&amp;amp;qid=1669070193&amp;amp;sprefix=bittersweet%2Caps%2C202&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;Bittersweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned that Grief is a natural reaction to Love that was taken away.  Grief cannot be fixed and it has no timeline.  Most people react to grief by trying to make it better.  You can never bring back my friends husband.  Sometimes people try to compare grief.  There’s no award for sadness.  In fact, the best way to address grief is to witness it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadness is interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Sadness triggers compassion.  It brings people together. . . The word compassion literally means ‘to suffer&lt;br /&gt;
together’ . . . The sadness from which compassion springs is a pro-social emotion, an agent of connection and
love; it’s what the musician Nick Cave calls ‘the universal unifying force.’  Sorrow and tears are one of the
strongest bonding mechanisms we have”  (Bittersweet, Susan Cain).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the midst of loss how do you comfort one another?  On Sunday we went to church.  Missy was mad at me because I was forcing the motions and not showing “empathy”.  In the quiet of the motions, bonding started to happen.  Prior to the service, Missy and Abby were able to quiet away a conversation on loss.  After the service, we were able to seek out prayer with a prayer leader which offered the palliative healing of confession.  Acknowledging our pain. Asking for help. Focus on what we wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In prayer I asked for the discernment to witness pain and be supportive.  To help without trying to fix the un-fixable.  To let our love be felt.  At the end of the prayer, Missy was a little misty eyed.  We also had greater appreciation of the task ahead of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After church, we ran Missy’s parents and Isaac to the house.  Abby, Missy, and myself made the trek to our friend.  There we sat, we snacked, and we talked.  Sometimes we remembered.  Sometimes we cried.  We talked about help.  We talked about space.  We hugged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the beginning of this process; but I think we were able to achieve our goal.  Now as life happens, I pray for grace that we remember what is important and keep that in the center of our life and outreach.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="faith" /><category term="heart" /><summary type="html">We recently lost a friend. More importantly our friends lost a father and a husband. In this post, I explore how the living try to continue the journey with love and compassion.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Personal Compass</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/faith/heart/Personal-Compass/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Personal Compass" /><published>2022-06-04T20:15:59-05:00</published><updated>2022-06-04T20:15:59-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/faith/heart/Personal-Compass</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/faith/heart/Personal-Compass/">&lt;p&gt;This weekend I had the opportunity to attend Pentecost mass at St. Xavier, the college church at St. Louis University.  The reflection after the mass encouraged celebrants to engage in Holy Spirit listening.  Because we’re often short of time, listening feels like a last art.  The leader of reflection related a story:  she attended a conference on listening and was reminded as our culture has embraced tribalism we’ve separated into two groups that reflect identity instead of just politics.  She recognized that she was afflicted as the speaker shared symbols associated with each group:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a MAGA cap&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a Black Lives Matter poster&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a Rainbow flag&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Confederate flag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we’re short for time, we talk in terms of labels; but like on a cup of soup, the label isn’t the same as the contents.  When we see a label we disagree with, we can stop listening especially if it triggers us.   In Thanks for the Feedback, Stone and Heen state that a common reason feedback is rejected is because it fires a truth trigger, a relationship trigger, or an identity trigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel this being liberal in Texas.  There are many times I’m at my kitchen table reminding my family that our neighbors can be good people even if they vote differently then us.  In fact, Daniel Pink shares in the Power of Regret that many of our moral differences occur “because one group has a narrower view of morality (don’t harm or cheat other people) and the other has a wider view (don’t harm or cheat other people—but also stay loyal to your group, heed authority, and uphold the sacred).”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to tap into “Holy Spirit Listening”, I think it’s very important to understand what you personally believe and to be curious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I planned for a job change earlier this year, I did some &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/my-core-values-integrity-heart-avi-sujeeth/?trackingId=Pd7VT73wG7D1OiJXKF46JA%3D%3D&quot;&gt;reflection&lt;/a&gt; on my core values: integrity and heart.  For me, it’s important to be my full-self in every aspect of my life.  When I see an apparent contradiction in my life or find others who have different values, I try to respond with curiosity - to seek to understand - to Holy Spirit Listen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve adopted framework’s across my political, religious, and science beliefs that I try glue together through rationalization into a tapestry that reflects my values.  The frameworks help me understand what I believe and what those beliefs state about my values - they become my personal compass.  Broadly I believe:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Politics is a social contract for the distribution of power.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Religion is a faith based expression of morality.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Science is a way of exploring the truth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;politics&quot;&gt;Politics&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human beings are social creatures.  In “Why Leaders Eat Last” Simon Sinek states early in our existence we learned that we were more effective with outside dangers by working together.  Through specialization and cooperation, we were able to thrive and ultimately change our conditions to suite our needs, creating a world of surplus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we went from groups of 150 people, to city states, to nations - we needed a social compact on how power was distributed.  Our political systems distribute power across dimensions of representativeness and arbitrariness.  Our economic systems distribute resources across dimensions of control and centralization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/avisuj/avisuj.github.io/blob/main/_includes/Political.JPG?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Political Quadrant Grid show Democracy (Elected, Rule of Law), Communism (Declared, Rule of Law), Fascism (Elected, Rule of Power), Dictatorship (Declared, Rule of Power)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/avisuj/avisuj.github.io/blob/main/_includes/Economic.JPG?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Economic Quadrant Grid show Socialism (Planned Economy, Distributed Economy), Capitalism (Market Economy, Distributed Economy), Aristocracy (Planned Economy, Centralized Economy), Oligarchy (Market Economy, Centralized Economy)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living in the United States, I think a governments effectiveness can be measured by the degree that it empowers all of its constituents to pursue life, liberty and happiness.  Often times, I think that means a government must be able to balance the sometimes conflicted needs of constituents in a way that is perceived as just and fair.  I believe systems that distribute power through the rule of law tend to be more resilient over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework allows me to go beyond the label associated with a government or an economic system to attempt to understand the values they represent.  When I find people who disagree with me, I try to be curious as to why they disagree:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does Communism mean something different to them?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are they advocating for the Rule of Power?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do they see a major value different between elected leaders and declared leaders?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework helps me go deeper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;religion&quot;&gt;Religion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an objectivist, I believe that moral truths exist.  I think living in alignment with these moral truths is living a Good Life. I think religion provides instruction around the moral truths and consequently makes it easier to live a Good Life.  As willing collaborators in God’s plan, we gain freedom from sin through the sacrifice of Jesus Christ.  Jesus calls us to love and in love we find our purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also think that is possible to live a Good Life by embracing a virtuous mindset regardless of faith.  For example, humanists are concerned with living a Good Life and will leverage the scientific method to reason what a Good Life looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The major religions have cultural codes that are captured in their texts, rituals, norms, and beliefs.  Rather than simply dismissing points of view I disagree with, I try to understand it in the full context of the religion.  I also try to evaluate if I think another religion more accurately describes what I believe to be morally true.   As US Bishops have started to deny communion to politicians for supporting the legalization of abortion, I’ve spent time reading the catechism, considering my beliefs, and talking to religious leaders and mentors.  In my microcosm, I have found that the Catholic Church continues to best reflect what I consider moral truth and my beliefs are also consistent with church teachings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;science&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his master class, Neil deGrasse Tyson describes the scientific method as “a problem solving approach that helps you glean reliable evidence in support of a hypothesis.”  It allows scientists to test ideas in the effort to identify the truth.  Scientists share and repeat these tests until there is no need to keep doing so.  After a test is completed, it is published in terms dictated by the scientific method:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;observation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;questions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hypothesis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;experiment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;result&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;conclusion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process allows for independent validation that roots out bias and mistakes.  I believe the truth discovered through the scientific method is useful like a landmark is to a person on voyage; it points to the right direction.  Therefore, I think it’s important to reconcile what we learn through science with my political and religious beliefs as it helps ensure that I’m actually making progress to the Good Life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to get lost in a meme.  It’s easy to respond to snark with sarcasm.  It’s much harder to learn from those that disagree with you.  It’s harder to listen with curiosity.  I use mental models as a way to deconstruct labels into implied values.  By staying curious, by leveraging the Holy Spirit to listen, I think my life is more rewarding because I can search for God in others and turn them into my teachers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="faith" /><category term="heart" /><summary type="html">It's easy to get lost in a meme. It's easy to respond to snark with sarcasm. It's much harder to learn from those that disagree with you. It's harder to listen with curiosity. In this blog post I talk about how I use mental models to deconstruct labels into implied values. By staying curious, by leveraging the Holy Spirit to listen, I think my life is more rewarding because I can search for God in others and turn them into my teachers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Communion</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/faith/parenting/Communion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Communion" /><published>2022-04-16T20:15:59-05:00</published><updated>2022-04-16T20:15:59-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/faith/parenting/Communion</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/faith/parenting/Communion/">&lt;p&gt;While I’ve talked about religion in the past, I haven’t deeply gone into my spiritual journey.  I’m going to in this post because I think it will be useful for me to resolve some apparent contradictions that from the outside maybe confusing.  For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why did I choose Catholicism when my wife was Episcopal and my mother was Hindu?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If I’m leading my children to be Catholic, why have I not gotten baptized?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do I resolve my liberal beliefs around abortion and homosexuality with the Catechism of the Church?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;god-is-love&quot;&gt;God is Love&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am an unbaptized Catholic.  I’ve had the privilege of having broad exposure to faiths: Catholicism, Protestantism, Hinduism, Buddhism, Judaism, and Islam.  As I strove to understand God, I found Christ’s message of love compelling.  I believe the two greatest commandments are: “You shall love the Lord your God with all your heart, and with all your soul, and with all your mind. . . [and] You shall love your neighbor as yourself” (Catechism of the Catholic Church).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I envision love, I imagine acceptance, protection, and warmth.  As Paul describes,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Love is patient, love is kind.  It does not envy, it does not boast, it is not proud.  It does not dishonor others, it is not self-seeking, it is not easily angered, it keeps no records of wrongs.  Love does not delight in evil but rejoices with the truth.  It always protects, always trusts, always hopes, always perseveres.  Love never fails (Corinthians 12:31 - 13:13).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love is creation, reconciliation, and grace.  Love is a virtue worth cherishing.  A God who loves is balm to the imperfect.  I feel God’s love when I see the awesome, see the holy, see the beautiful, and prey to God; for me it feels like energy goes through me creating a warm buzz in my brain.  I remember first having this experience while attending mass in high school.  I remember associating the feeling with God during a senior retreat called Kairos, a three day student led retreat about self-discovery and developing a personal relationship with God.  At one point in the retreat, we were provided letters from friends and family that we read and shared with others.  I was surprised to receive a letter from my parents; my high school years were tumultuous as my emo self struggled with a feeling of unworthiness that was complicated by untreated depression.  I didn’t think I had earned my parents love.  In the letter, my parents acknowledged the strife we had experienced but reinforced that they were proud of me and loved me.  In that moment, I felt God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last few weeks, I’ve been dealing with a depression flare-up that has encouraged me to face feelings of shame and worthlessness.  At one point, I called my doctor to describe thoughts of suicide and the nurse who answered commended me for being aware that the feelings were irrational.  Love centers me; I know my family, friends, and God loves me.  I’ve learned to trust that love as a flashlight in the darkness and use it to separate reality from what I feel in depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps because of my own struggles, I also understand the value of shared suffering.  In a world of God’s love, we are still far away from heaven on earth.  There is pain; sometimes attributable to free will and at other times, as with childhood cancer, seemingly unexplainable.  To me, the idea that God would choose to experience our suffering in order to model what we should strive for reflects a love that’s observable through sacrifice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;God has honored you. The gospel is the story of how he did it. At the heart of the story is the word servant. Jesus Christ became your servant. . . When Jesus voluntarily became your servant, he lowered himself and elevated you (Shame Interrupted).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we were looking for churches, Missy and I started looking at Episcopal churches.  I noticed some very small differences in the church; probably the most obvious was the focus on the Cross as opposed to the Crucifix.  In philosophy and religious studies in College, I learned to pay attention to these differences.  Differences can help you understand what people have experienced in the past.  For example, the Gospel of Mathew’s focus on lineage contrasts with the Gospel of Luke’s unique parables speak to their respective audiences, Jews and Gentiles.  Whitewashing differences denies individuals their truth, limits our ability to empathize, and prevents our ability to seek justice.  We all have a past.  While our past doesn’t control our future, it does need to be recognized.  Similarly, the focus on the Cross verse Crucifix reflects a theological focus on the resurrection or the passion.  Acceptance of suffering is an important message for me; significant enough that I had a strong preference for the Catholic Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;unbaptized-catholic&quot;&gt;unbaptized catholic&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if I’m an unapologetic Catholic, why don’t I get baptized?  To be honest, I’m looking forward to re-evaluating this decision in counseling.  In the past, I’ve decided not to get baptized because my mom would prefer if I didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my mom first found out I was thinking about converting, she took to me India to learn more about Hinduism.  I learned the core Hindu values are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brahman - The One God.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Atman - God’s expression of creation that exists in individuals.  There is God in all of us.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dharma - The essence of God that makes an individual.  By honoring our essence, we can become one with God.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Karma - A connective experience that unites all of our individual lives and gives us the ability to reunite with the One God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I envision the God of Hinduism as a loving light.  Through love, light creates.  Creation retains a portion of the One God’s light that can be realized when the individual lives in a way that is consistent with God’s essence.  Upon death, the individual rejoins God unless something they experienced in their current life blocks them.  In the event they are blocked, they are shown mercy and given an opportunity to try again in a new life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As my mom pointed out to me, that core belief structure is compatible with following Jesus Christ as a Guru.  In fact, there was a portrait of Jesus in the Hare Krishna Hare Rama temple that Missy and I got married in (for those keeping track Missy and I have been married four times).  Several of my family members have a portrait of Jesus on their personal altars.  It’s a type of whitewashing that acknowledges the message of love Jesus preached while ignoring his Jewish heritage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve grown older my mom’s objections to conversion have varied; but ultimately it boils down to she’s concerned about the judgement of our family and her community.  To date, I have chosen to honor my mother wishes.  I have participated in the church by attending weekly without receiving sacraments.  In this way, I am trying to model behavior for my children as they grow up in the church.  One day, I’ll likely get baptized and join my family fully in the church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;cafeteria-catholic&quot;&gt;cafeteria catholic&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December 2020, I reached out to friends on Facebook because I was struggling with the news that the United States Conference of Catholic Bishops was considering denying Joe Biden communion on the basis of his pro-choice position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abortion is a serious decision that is often made in imperfect situations where there isn’t a good option.  I had a friend who found she was pregnant six months into a relationship with an older man.  She wasn’t ready to be a mother and their relationship wasn’t stable enough to raise a child.  After discussing the pregnancy with her partner, she decided to get an abortion.  I saw the way that decision impacted her and the pain she went through during the procedure.  It wasn’t easy.  I’m glad that I didn’t have to face that decision.  I supported my friend the best I could by being present and not judging her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly one out of three single mothers in the United States live in poverty.  It’s not easy; as a society we don’t provide access to affordable child care and many jobs don’t provide the flexibility single mothers need.  We can do better and if we did I’m convinced abortions would decrease.  In fact, I think aid programs explain the correlation between Democratic presidents and the decrease in abortion rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Catholic church is clear that abortion is evil.  My experience with abortion reflects that, abortion hurts everyone involved and should not be celebrated.  As with most impossible decisions, I think the decision should be made by the people directly involved.  The church states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A person who procures a completed abortion incurs excommunication latae sententiae, by the very commission of the offense . . . The moment a positive law deprives a category of human beings of the protection which civil legislation ought to accord them, the state is denying the equality of all before the law. When the state does not place its power at the service of the rights of each citizen, and in particular of the more vulnerable, the very foundations of a state based on law are undermined (Catechism of the Catholic Church).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same token, the church provides for legitimate defense:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The legitimate defense of persons and societies is not an exception to the prohibition against the murder of the innocent that constitutes intentional killing. “The act of self-defense can have a double effect: the preservation of one’s own life; and the killing of the aggressor. The one is intended, the other is not.”  Love toward oneself remains a fundamental principle of morality. Therefore it is legitimate to insist on respect for one’s own right to life (Catechism of the Catholic Church).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further even grave sins can be forgiven:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Certain particularly grave sins incur excommunication, the most severe ecclesiastical penalty, which impedes the reception of the sacraments and the exercise of certain ecclesiastical acts, and for which absolution consequently cannot be granted, according to canon law, except by the Pope, the bishop of the place or priests authorized by them (Catechism of the Catholic Church).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides abortion, I struggle with the churches teachings on homosexuality.  I find the call for abstinence unrealistic and inappropriate.  I take solace that church also says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The number of men and women who have deep-seated homosexual tendencies is not negligible. This inclination, which is objectively disordered, constitutes for most of them a trial. They must be accepted with respect, compassion, and sensitivity. Every sign of unjust discrimination in their regard should be avoided. These persons are called to fulfill God’s will in their lives and, if they are Christians, to unite to the sacrifice of the Lord’s Cross the difficulties they may encounter from their condition (Catechism of the Catholic Church).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My eight grade religious teacher was gay.  I’m grateful for him.  Two lessons stood out to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He related a story from his grandmother who asked him when he had cut himself, “what color is your blood?”  When he answered red, his grandmother reminded him that regardless of difference everyone’s blood is red.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He pointed out to the class that homosexuality maybe viewed as a sin but so was birth control and masturbation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the Church’s teachings identify that I’m in a sinful relationship with my wife because I’ve had vasectomy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“every action which, whether in anticipation of the conjugal act, or in its accomplishment, or in the development of its natural consequences, proposes, whether as an end or as a means, to render procreation impossible” is intrinsically evil (Catechism of the Catholic Church).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I struggle with the teachings, I pray for discernment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to understand if the focus on abortion and homosexuality is misplaced in the context of Christ’s teachings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to understand if, like Judas, I’m trying to exert my will over God’s will.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you join a community based on values, you don’t get to opt out of values that you struggle with.  I recognize that the decision making power on church teachings rest with the clergy.  At the same time, even a piece criticizing Cardinal Marx for calling for the Catechism’s teaching on homosexuality to be changed recognized:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Catechism isn’t above question or critique, but such inquiries should challenge not what the Catechism teaches but, rather, how it teaches it. The Catechism is, after all, for catechesis, and as such it can fall short in conveying what the Church has established, but this does not affect the holy tradition of truth behind it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think of Jesus going to prostitutes, going to lepers, and going to adulterers.  I find it hard to believe that Jesus would shun people for these violations of the Ten Commandments.  As the catechism says, “it is in the New Covenant in Jesus Christ that their [The Ten Commandments] full meaning would be revealed” (Catechism of the Catholic Church).  Ultimately, I think it’s up to the sinner to resolve his or her sin with God through reconciliation.  Regardless, sin does not grant me the power to judge others.  Likewise, sin does not give me the power to deny others love; one cannot be too stingy with love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-stay&quot;&gt;why stay&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think as the Church’s sex abuse crisis has shown, the Church is not without sin.  We are all doing our best to live a Good Life that was modeled by Jesus Christ.  In 2022, there’s a great deal of sorting that serves to isolate ourselves from diverse perspectives.  Rather than respectfully engaging with people we disagree with, we quit.  I think it’s a tragedy that weaponizes our differences.  It’s certainly not in alignment with the vision of the church as a field hospital for sinners.  I think the struggle with these issues, like a knife grinding on a whetstone, can make the community and individuals better.  I’m confident that the church’s teachings have made me a better person, a better father, and a better husband.  In addition, as a member of the church if I can help someone feel welcome, who otherwise would feel threatened out of place, then I feel like I’m doing God’s work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="faith" /><category term="parenting" /><summary type="html">In Communion, I talk about my faith journey. Specifically I try to answer: +Why I chose Catholicism when my wife was Episcopal and my mother was Hindu? +If I'm leading my children to be Catholic, why have I not gotten baptized? +How do I resolve my liberal beliefs around abortion and homosexuality with the Catechism of the Church?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Armor</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/legacy/Armor/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Armor" /><published>2022-04-11T20:15:59-05:00</published><updated>2022-04-11T20:15:59-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/legacy/Armor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/legacy/Armor/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve started counseling to explore the bittersweet of my soul that surfaces in depression.  It’s my hope through reflection that I’m able to make space with sadness; to make depression less of a thing that I keep locked away until it breaks it’s cage and more of an aspect of personality that I live with and manage.  To that end, I gave my counselor three goals that I wanted to work on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to explore the armor I put around health issues because I think it can prevent me from empathizing with people in pain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to reflect on my need to belong and the boundaries I’ve established in creating my tribe, my family, my work, and my spirituality.  While I think I’m mainly balanced, I think it’s helpful to have check-up because unhealthy behavior is amazingly easy to rationalize away.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to explore the shame I carry for things that I’ve done in my past.  I want to understand the source, any feeding behaviors I may have, and the impact that carrying weight may have on decision making.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the first counseling session, I agreed to reflect more on the issues I have with health issues; I agreed to identify underlying causes and consider what if anything I would be willing to change in my behavior.  So while this post is primarily targeted at that discovery, I think it’ll be useful if I setup some context about me before we dive in together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;background&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My core values are heart and integrity.  For me living with a whole heart means that I give everything I have and more to situations that I find myself in.  Integrity balances my leave-it-on-the-field drive by encouraging self-awareness, candor, and a growth-mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a doer.  If you were to drop me in the middle of the wilderness, I would start walking in a uniform direction because the probability that I’d find a road is high.  I’d try to learn about my surroundings to determine what I would need to do make it back to civilization and start executing on that plan.  In addition to ambiguous situations, I’ll work through almost anything that’s difficult; when the going get’s tough, I get going.  For example, after my wife and I got married, I insisted that we do Sunday night dinners with my parents.  After my dad decided not to attend our wedding, I knew that those dinners would be difficult and there would be many years ahead of repairing the relationship between the family I was creating and my parents.  Nevertheless, I was determined to do my part by showing up.  Having lived with unmedicated depression for nearly thirty years; I think I became a doer because if I stayed still when I was in trouble, I would have drowned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rely on feedback systems to ensure that my effort is well-invested and my effort results in outcomes I associate with living a good life.  Every month I track my weight, sleep, activity, church attendance, dates and other kpi’s.  When I don’t feel satisfied, I try to reflect on proximate causes and things I can do to improve.  I talk to my tribe about difficulty I’m going through.  I read voraciously to learn about new ideas.  As a result, I don’t just do; I get better.  I continually try to become the person I want to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fpr most of my life, I couldn’t imagine that people would deal with adversity in other ways.  When Yammer got acquired by Microsoft, my doer drive was in full swing.  I quickly learned the territory I was going to be responsible for, determined an initial travel schedule, and made contact with teams that I’d support.  In contrast, several of my peers waited for clarification about the role and suggested initiatives before engaging.  Trying to understand the difference, I talked to a mentor who reminded me that sometimes people respond to uncertainty by searching for more information.  We talked about the reasons why that’s an appropriate response: with more information you gain confidence in your direction, with more information you can coordinate your actions with others, and with more information you can leverage the sponsorship of others to move faster.  While the approach was foreign, it was a revelation because I could empathize with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in my career I’d partner with a client executive who would push this concept with me further.  He pointed out that activity doesn’t always generate results; in fact, results correlated when clients could articulate the value of the activity.  He showed me that timing mattered and that sometimes it was best to move at the same speed as the client you were working with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a doer but I also recognize that it’s important to move at the speed of those that I’m working with.  Now, I am being challenged to apply this professional lesson to my personal life in order to better empathize with people who are in pain.  It’s probably not a surprise that I deal with pain by “shaking it off”.  I tend to respond to others in pain with the same type of guidance.  Unfortunately, that’s one of least effective ways to respond to pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;responding-to-pain&quot;&gt;responding to pain&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The human soul doesn’t want to be advised or fixed or saved.  It simply wants to be witnessed, exactly as it is.  Parker Palmer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a video, Megan Devine explains how acknowledgement is the best way to help those suffering; to sit with others who are in pain and not try to fix it.  People are resilient, they’ll find their own path forward.  Acknowledging where they are helps them feel validated and supported.  For me the line between acknowledgement and acceptance is blurry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my youth, my dad didn’t draw lines between punishment, anger, and love.  As a result, I felt that love was conditional.  That was reinforced by what I saw with my parents relationship.  While they never actually divorced, they came close several times.  Most often the fights were about money and I internalized them as: I will love you if you can reduce your wasteful spending.  One time it got so bad, I actually helped my mom put a down-payment on an apartment.  After each argument, my parents reconciled in private which appeared to me as acceptance of the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mom was born with CMT4; she didn’t start walking until she was five.  She’s on several heart medications to manage a weak heart beat.  She has a bulging eye that’s impacted her vision.  While my parents’ arguments were about money, I always felt like health wasn’t far away.  The spending my dad would complain about included spending on medication and massages to manage pain.  I learned that love could be contingent on a persons ability to deal with pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my first committed relationship, I dated a person who lived with Crohn’s disease.  She was in severe pain and struggled.  Over the course of two years, she had her intestines re-sectioned four times ultimately culminating colectomy.  It was painful watching someone I care about, someone who had dreams, lose herself to the pain associated with disease.  I stayed in that relationship too long, in the end sacrificing my undergraduate experience.  As it became clear that she was becoming ill, I tried to accelerate my study so that I could take on the role of the bread-winner.  I ended graduating before I was 20 and ran up an impressive amount of debt trying to make the failed relationship work.  As I saw her fail, I tried to setup a series of positive incentives to encourage her to figure out how to manage her disease.  I even agreed to get married if we could make our lives financially sustainable.  I was trying to setup conditions for my love that could manipulate how my then fiance managed pain.  I wanted her to take control of her life on my timetable; in exchange I would love her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When that relationship ended, I was sad because I felt like I had failed; but I was confident that the relationship had on a whole made me a worse person.  I had learned how to survive and had some great memories but I wasn’t progressing towards a good life.  I determined that I had tried to take responsibility for another person’s choices and thus had setup a relationship based on a house of cards.  In the future, I vowed to only enter relationships on mutual respect; as a partnership of equals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;shutting-down&quot;&gt;shutting down&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my engagement with Missy, she had multiple minor surgeries for what was diagnosed as a Bartholin cyst.  While she was going through that, I couldn’t help but see a similarity to my previous experience with Crohn’s.  I distinctly remember at one point talking to Missy’s brother after she had been admitted to the hospital; I told him I wasn’t sure if I go through another relationship affected by Crohn’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I determined then, as now, that Missy’s support makes me a better person.  She encourages me to do difficult things and she has faith that together we can tackle any challenge.  Her steadiness helps anchor me and provides a base for me to relate with others.  She makes me better; I wasn’t going to give that up for Crohn’s.  At the same token, I was committed to not make the same mistakes that I made in my previous relationship.  Through couple’s counseling I learned how to voice disagreements, define boundaries, and practice unconditional love.  I learned that I could love and support Missy without taking ownership of her problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One boundary I quickly established was around health.  I’d support her and be present when she needed to have a procedure; but I wouldn’t sacrifice my future.  She accepted the limits of support I could provide and she developed her own support network of family and friends that would help her through medical crisis.  In fact, shortly after I got a job offer from Microsoft, Missy was formally diagnosed with Crohn’s and required a major surgery.  As timing would have it, I moved to Minnesota weeks before her surgery.  Through the support of her parents, she got through the surgery and recovered and was able to join me three months later.  In order to protect myself, I would love and support her but I wouldn’t sacrifice experiences for her health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our marriage continued, the boundary worked for us in a large part because her parents are incredibly supportive and could fill this gap that I couldn’t.  Over time, Missy pointed out boundary creep - not only did I not sacrifice but I also was cold to her when she complained about pain.  I would tell her that she needed to figure it out and manage her health.  Eventually she did, becoming an amazing example of what a self-advocating patient looks like.  At the same time, it turned out that the boundary I established around health applied not just to Missy but everyone in my life including our children.  I’m definitely not the parent that will bring you soup in bed when you are sick.  I find that I have some distance with those that I love because I don’t empathize with their suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;going-forward&quot;&gt;going forward&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to close that distance.  I want to support those that I care about.  “The real barrier  . . . is our armor - the thoughts, emotions and behaviors that we use to protect ourselves when we aren’t willing and able to rumble with vulnerability,” Brene Brown says in Daring Leadership.  She continues, “When we stop caring about what anyone thinks, we’re too armored for authentic connection.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Brown also provides an approach for moving forward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rather than protecting and hiding our heart behind bulletproof glass, wholeheartedness is about integration, It’s integrating our thinking, feeling, and behavior.  It’s putting down the armor and bringing forth all of the scraggly, misshapen pieces of our history and folding in all of the different roles that, when falsely separated, keep us feeling exhausted and torn, to make a complex, messy, awesome whole person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me this blog, is an attempt to integrate the compartments of myself.  I’m trying to undergo sense-making of the things I’m passionate about to better understand who I am and inform how I want to live in the future.  In her book, Dr. Brown provides sixteen examples of armor and provides some suggestions on how to put down armor.  Several things flag up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Numbing - the act of leveraging an activity or an addiction to take the edge off pain.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Counter: Sent boundaries and Finding Real Comfort - Broadly defining boundaries is making clear what’s okay and what’s not okay, and why.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hiding Behind Cynicism - expressing frustration through passive-aggressiveness and sarcasm.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Counter: Modeling Clarity, Kindness, and Hope - Say what you mean and mean what you say.  Have a goal, a path. and confidence that it can be achieved.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using Criticism as Protection - Criticism shifts the spotlight off us and onto someone or something else.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Counter: Make Contributions and Take Risks - Come with a point of view and be prepared ot share it.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zigzagging and Avoiding - Zigzagging is a metaphor for trying to dodge the bullets of vulnerability
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Counter: Talking Straight and Taking Action - Bring clarity and awareness to what we’re trying to avoid - then get clear about what needs to be done.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to be able to establish clearer boundaries between acknowledgement and acceptance.  One way I can establish the boundaries is by changing how I react; rather than trying to solve a problem I can be better about responding with curiosity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It sounds like you are dealing with pain, do you want to talk about it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you have a plan to make your situation better?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How can I best support you?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can also set boundaries around how other peoples processes affect me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I understand your suffering right now, but I need a plan.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am going to act because I think it will make the situation better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if this path will lead to success; I do think it’s an attempt to be better.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="heart" /><category term="integrity" /><category term="legacy" /><summary type="html">I work through a mental block that I have around empathizing with other's illness. I talk about how my personality, and my past contribute to that block and I discuss hopes I have for changing my behavior in the future.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Other</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/legacy/Other/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Other" /><published>2022-03-29T20:15:59-05:00</published><updated>2022-03-29T20:15:59-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/legacy/Other</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/legacy/Other/">&lt;p&gt;The first time I felt like an other was when I was in second grade.  The kids in my public school were having a hard time pronouncing Avinash so they took to a nickname - Carwash.  Around the same time, I had a south asian friend who nicknamed me Avi.  I felt like I had a choice; I could become Carwash or I could become Avi.  After watching the Simpsons, I resolved to do whatever it took to be distant from the Kwik-E-Mart, Gas Stations, and Carwashes.  And so Avi was born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being the other was also reinforced by an early childhood trip to India.  During music class at school; we were taught a refrain to sing back after kids sang “Happy Birthday”.  In that trip, my family celebrated my birthday.  I sang the refrain as I was taught.  The reaction I got let me know what I had done wasn’t a norm in my family.  The lesson I learned was that I was too Indian to be American and too American to be Indian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, I don’t think that was the appropriate lesson; I’m friends with many of my first cousins and I’m grateful for my global family.  I think the challenge I had and still have is this pursuit to feel like I belong.  For my kids - I’ve tried to get ahead of this by helping them build relationships with extended family, by talking to them about race, and by leaning on other structures that can reinforce belonging like religion.  I want them to feel like they are 100% Indian and 100% American.  I want them to have a sense that they belong to this world, this family, and they can leverage their history to help them become who they want to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a small friend circle of South Asians growing up, I eventually developed an identity as a minority.  Not having an accent or speaking Malayalam made it difficult to find commonalities with kids at the temple.  What’s worse, as a minority trying to assimilate - I judged the kids that I viewed as Indian.  At least I wasn’t Apu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My minority identity was eventually challenged when, at 16, I was in downtown St. Louis.   I tried to act as an ally to a black man.  While I don’t remember the exact situation; I do remember that the man quickly pointed out to me that I wasn’t black.  That realization was reinforced as I started to become aware of the privilege I had grown up in; I felt like while I was an other I didn’t carry the burden required to be a minority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I love about my wife is that I always felt that she saw me as a person.  In fact, she didn’t realize she was in a mixed race relationship until we were driving in a wealthy neighborhood in St. Louis and I was pulled over by a police officer.  The officer asked my wife if she was ok before letting us go.  That year I was pulled over and released over five times.  In hindsight, I think it likely had to do with a problem with my license registration.  All the same, none of the officers provided me with an explanation of why I was being pulled over.  Without that information, what I learned was that while I wasn’t a minority, I definitely wasn’t the majority either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the relationship with my wife deepened, we decided to get married.  Our engagement was difficult.  Neither of us were financially secure.  My parents frowned on the marriage because they felt like we were doing ourselves an injustice in trying to build a house on a shaky foundation.  When my dad told me he wasn’t going to attend the wedding, I was devastated.  I told him that we would get beyond any short term decision but that some decisions you couldn’t take back.  I want to be clear that I love my parents and I think they were trying to protect our new family.  We didn’t need protection; we needed support.  In part because of my dad’s decision, none of my extended family attended the wedding either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I wonder if Avinash still exists or if all that’s left is Avi.  I get angry at my younger self for making such an important decision about identity out of a desire for acceptance that feels like it will never be realized.  I wonder if Avinash would have had more family at his wedding.  At the same token, I don’t think that’s the right question for me to ask.  I can’t control the past.  I feel like I should ask if I am growing to be the person I want to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook reminded me that I once wondered if a person is more than the sum of their past experiences.  In addition to the past, I think determining where you want to go is important.  I am confident that I’m trying to make the best of my talents to realize God’s commandment that we love each other.  If Avi can get me to where I want to go, do I still need Avinash?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently in my professional career, I had a few South Asian friends clue me in on an acronym ABCD - American Born Confused Desi.  For the record, I was born in India and had to go through the naturalization process with the help of a lawyer.  All the same, I suppose it should be comforting that there are enough people who share my desire to belong that we have an acronym.  Unfortunately, it just reminds me that I’m outside of communities that I want to be part of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my wife read this post, she said “we are our own other group.”  I’m reminded of the Fault of the Stars:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think your special is that not enough?  You think the ony way to lead a meaningful life is for everyone to remember you.  For everyone to love you.  Guess what, Gus. This is your life, okay?  This is all you get.  You get me, and you get your family, and you get this world, and that’s it.  And if that’s not enough for you then I’m sorry but it’s not nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="heart" /><category term="integrity" /><category term="legacy" /><summary type="html">I've struggled with belonging since I was young. The desire to belong has driven me for so long that I think it's a major part of my identify. In this blog post, I talk about that desire nad how it's affected who I am right now. I suspect, if I'm honest with myself, the desire to belong is underneath the anger and self-deprecation that exacerbates my depression.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Red Lines</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/Red-Lines/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Red Lines" /><published>2022-03-25T20:15:59-05:00</published><updated>2022-03-25T20:15:59-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/Red-Lines</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/Red-Lines/">&lt;p&gt;This week I saw my doctor related to my depression because I crossed a red line.  On Wednesday, as I was waking I thought wouldn’t it be easier if I reached the end of my journey.  The self exploration could stop.  The pain associated with shame could stop.  Moreover, I know how to end my journey.  Previous research has taught me how to suicide and I could picture it - sliced wrists or dying while street cycling.  Picturing your suicide is not normal and for me it’s a particular red line that indicates my normal coping mechanisms are not working and I need help.  With my doctor, we decided to increase the dosage of my antidepressant medication and in addition I signed up for talkspace to gain access to psychologist to work through this flareup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year while going through Dare to Lead training professionally, I learned that “setting boundaries is making clear what’s okay and what’s not okay, and why.  Vulnerability minus boundaries is not vulnerability.  It’s confession, manipulation, desperation, or shock and awe, but it’s not vulnerability” (Dare to Lead).  While boundaries are clearly important in relationships, I think they are equally important in how I manage myself.  So much of life is habit driven inertia; by being clear about the boundaries that I think are acceptable I can get signs about when I need to act; when just trying to push through isn’t the right answer.  These are my red lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In looking at Cleveland Clinic’s symptoms of depression, I now manifest three of eight common symptoms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feeling very sad, hopeless or worried&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not enjoying things that used to give you joy ✔️&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being easily irritated or frustrated&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eating too much or too little&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changes in how much you sleep ✔️&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having a difficult time concentrating or remembering things&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experiencing physical problems like headache, stomachache, or sexual dysfunction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thinking about hurting or killing yourself ✔️&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever this is, it’s clear to me that it’s not a simple passing sadness.  I’m confident that the steps I’m taking with my medical team will help me restore balance.  While I’m in this sadness, I want to take the opportunity for self-reflection to determine if there is something I’m longing for that has made me welcome this sorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Why do we sometimes welcome sorrow when the rest of the time we will quite naturally do anything we can to avoid 
it?  There’s actually a scholarly debate raging over this question, but I have come to believe that really, what 
we are craving, at bottom, is that state of longing, that joy that’s laced with sorrow. Which is often triggered 
when we experience something so exquisite that it seems to come to us from some other world (The hidden power of 
sad songs and rainy days)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I have some theories about what I might be longing for, I don’t find any completely satisfactory:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to be able to forgive myself.  There’s some truth to this.  I am harder on myself then anyone else would even dream to be.  I also carry some secrets that I’m not proud of.  I blame myself for things that are outside of my control.  At the same token, I’m proud of my life.  I’m proud of the impact I have on my family, colleagues, and the world at large.  While I see the world as imperfect, I also think I’m working with others to make it better.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to unify myself.  In many ways, I’ve reacted to living with depression by compartmentalizing it.  I’ve kept my life in neat boxes and I don’t give room often to the angst-y child who wanted above all other things to be normal.  Banishing that boy has consequences.  It has made it harder for me to empathize with people who are in pain.  As a result, in the face of someone elses suffering I can come off as cold.  Likewise I’ve surprised as aspects of my life have been claimed by other communities.  For example, when I was doing inclusivity work last year I was surprised that the community I was working with acknowledged my history with depression as living with a disability.  Because I don’t allow it to be part of me, I struggle recognizing myself as part of a community.  I’m denying myself connection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This to me is core to the meaning of life: To decide who you are, who you want to be, and what steps you need to take to get there.  I don’t know the answers but I’m confident that the journey taking is a better reaction than trying to simply banish the dark.  I look forward to the next steps I take in establishing this new more complete identity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="heart" /><category term="integrity" /><summary type="html">I crossed a red line in my journey with depression this week. I'm taking steps to get extra assistance. I'm confident that the steps I'm taking will help me restore balance. At the same token, I'm not simply trying to banish depression from my life as I have in the past. I don't know what the answers are but I look forward to the next steps I take in establishing this new more complete identity.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Institutionalized</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/Institutionalized/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Institutionalized" /><published>2022-03-18T20:15:59-05:00</published><updated>2022-03-18T20:15:59-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/Institutionalized</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/Institutionalized/">&lt;p&gt;My cheeks were flushed.  I was embarrassed; the people in my dorm were laughing at me.  They all were laughing at me.  As I caught a breadth, I realized that was ridiculous and then I got mad.  Shortly after I started college, I agreed with a psychiatrist to start on a selective Serotonin re-uptake inhibitor.  I thought it was supposed to keep me from feeling this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve struggled with depression my entire life; early in that struggle I also carried shame associated with being on medication.  I rationalized that medication was provided to people to fix an acute brokenness.  In this case, my brokenness was the way I think.  It was supposed to prevent me from thinking irrational thoughts.  It was supposed to keep me happy or at the least dull the familiar ache of pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that’s not the way medication works.  Serotonin re-uptake inhibitors make it easier for the active transport of Serotonin through cells.  They mitigate a biological trait that prevents normal transport of Serotonin.  It doesn’t work like other mind altering drugs that simulate pleasure chemicals.  As a result, being on anti-depressant doesn’t eliminate pain or embarrassment; it just helps me keep perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the moment, in my anguish and my desire to end how I was feeling; I took the entire bottle.  It started as a test to see how many pills would it take to dull the pain.  When it didn’t improve after taking another hit, it just seemed natural to double down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My roommate got assistance from the floor supervisor who called the police.  Two EMT’s entered our dorm room, put me on a stretcher, and wheeled me to an ambulance.  I remember looking at the faces of the people who were around me - I remember seeing a look of concern; a look of pity coming from those watching the scene that I had unintentionally caused.  I felt pitiful; I felt worthless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next thing I remember, I was in the emergency room at St. Louis University Hospital.  The doctor fed me chalk to dilute anything I may have taken.  Their biggest concern was that I wasn’t a reliable witness in my state.  They were afraid that I had taken something else in addition to the bottle of anti-depressants.  They expected that I had taken something else.  I chuckled to myself, I wasn’t even good enough to correctly attempt suicide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I woke up on the psychiatric floor.  I asked to get discharged and I was told that I was going to be in observation for at least 72 hours.  I remember feeling trapped.  The hospital floor was clean like all hospital floors but it was warmer; the walls were beige - the air didn’t smell like antiseptic.  It wasn’t the scene that One Flew Over the Cuckoo’s Nest had prepared me for.  Like other hospital floors, there was a nursing station and a shared room where patients mingled with each other.  It felt like no-one visited the psychiatric floor; after all who would.  I don’t remember much about my time on the floor.  I didn’t feel like I had a lot in common with my fellow patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember talking to a psychologist who evaluated me.  The conversations were short; he was trying to figure out if I knew where I was, what had happened, and what would happen next.  I tried to talk about how medication made me feel uncomfortable.  I quickly learned if I struggled against medication, I wasn’t going to get released.  I finally answered his questions the way I thought he wanted me to - I was rewarded with a nod and discharge orders.  The day after I was released, I picked up the medication I was prescribed.  As I left the hospital medication in hand, I walked to the nearest public trash can and threw the pills away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this moment in my life, I’ve learned a lot.  I ended up making peace with medication nearly 10 years later.  I think moments of struggle are also invitations to grow and sometimes growth takes a long time.  As I’m writing this - I’m tempted to compare my struggle with those of others; there’s a part of me that doesn’t feel like I deserve to tell this story.  However as a good friend reminded me, comparison is the thief of happiness; struggle is struggle and grief is grief.  It’s personal and isn’t minimized because other grief or struggle exists.  I’m retelling my struggle to own it.  It is part of me but it doesn’t define who I am.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="heart" /><category term="integrity" /><summary type="html">When I was 17, I was committed to St. Louis University Hospital for 72 hours. I'm retelling my struggle to own it. It is part of me but it doesn't define who I am. I think moments of struggle are also invitations to grow; and sometimes growth takes a long time. As I'm writing this - I'm tempted to compare my struggle with those of others; there's a part of me that doesn't feel like I deserve to tell this story. However as a good friend reminded me, comparison is the thief of happiness; struggle is struggle and grief is grief. It's personal and isn't minimized because other grief or struggle exists.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Depression</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/Depression/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Depression" /><published>2022-03-12T19:15:59-06:00</published><updated>2022-03-12T19:15:59-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/Depression</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/heart/integrity/Depression/">&lt;p&gt;As I awake this morning, my eyes are wet and my chest is heavy.  I feel like I’ve been crying for a week; which I have been.  Two weeks ago, my daughter caught Covid-19 from school.  We were expecting it - she went to a school band lock-in; with a concentration of middle-schoolers indoors it seemed inevitable.  I ended up showing symptoms on March 4th.  Fortunately, our entire experience of Covid-19 has been mild and we tested negative for it yesterday.  I didn’t expect that I’d get caught up in a depression flare-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was diagnosed with depression when I was 16.  I’ve been on and off medication five times in my life; recently accepting that I will always need medication to help manage the physical symptoms of the disorder.  My mental photographs of childhood center around meltdowns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There was the time I let my brother take the fall for me for creating a mess in the dining room.  He got spanked; I got the shame.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There was the time when my dad was consoling me through uncontrollable sadness while visiting a family in Ohio.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There was the time when I got invited to the cool kids birthday party and I awkwardly stood out.  I blamed my parents for that with white hot anger that reflected into personal shame.  What kind of child carries that kind of anger?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There was the time when I was committed to the hospital for suicide watch.  That moment was wondrous shame mix - I was ashamed of having a condition; I was ashamed of being on medication; and I was ashamed of getting rejected by a girl.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Mayo Clinic, “Depression is a mood disorder that causes persistent feeling of sadness and loss of interest. . . Recent research indicates that changes in the function and effect of these neurotransmitters and how they interact with neurocircuits involved in maintaining mood stability may play a significant role in depression and its treatment.”  I remember studying facilitated transport in biology - I picture myself short on receptors for Serotonin.  Simon Sinek writes: “Serotonin is the feeling of pride. It is the feeling we get when we perceive that others like or respect us. It makes us feel strong and confident, like we can take on anything. . . Serotonin is attempting to reinforce the bond between parent and child, teacher and student, coach and player, boss and employee, leader and follower.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a condition that encourages me to carry shame instead of pride; to focus on sadness instead of happiness; to embrace grief instead of connection.  I suspect my mental photographs reflect this tendency.  It’s easier for me to recall sadness.  The medication I’m on to treat depression is a selective Serotonin re-uptake inhibitor.  It helps me balance shame with pride and sadness with joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve gotten older, it has become easier for me to tell when I’m driving my life or if my disorder is.  When I’m struggling with Serotonin deficiency:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I will be quick to anger; often being viewed by others as mercurial in disagreements.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I will be overwhelmed by negative self-talk.  I will only see disaster and destruction around me.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I will isolate myself to hide my shame.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emotions do not exist in a vacuum; in the past I’ve struggled with my disorder in moments of change in my environment.  For example, with this flare-up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spring has been unseasonably late&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ukraine has been invaded by Russia&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My family caught Covid-19&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trigger for this episode was the death of a fictional character.  Last week, while I was sick I binged on the Divergent series.  In the last book, the heroine of this war-ravaged world dies saving it in an act of loving self-sacrifice.  Veronica Roth comments “In each book she [the heroine] tried to emulate her parents sacrifice [her parents died saving her life], and in each book she didn’t seem to understand what sacrifice really was until Allegiant.  And it’s only in Allegiant when she has a strong sense of identity, when she had a keen understanding of what she believed about selflessness, that her journey was over.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sad because I’m displacing my life onto the heroine’s.  While I read the book as part of an effort to escape the feeling of hopelessness associated with the Ukraine war, I recognize that the book is fiction; that it’s an escape.  I’m sad because at this moment I’m predisposed to only see the loss.  For me, that is depression - reacting in an unreasonable way because I’m temporarily blinded from the beauty of life.  I know it’s there but I can’t see it and in my blindness I embrace things I do see; shame, grief, and sadness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, the embrace feels good.  It feels good to feel.  I think it has given me an emotional outlet for the stress of the things that have been happening in the world over the last month.  I’m grateful for it.  It’s ok to not be ok.  It’s equally important to continue.  Emily Black concludes her book Sanctuary with a story about a dog who had finally broken free from a stake he was chained to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I could no longer see him but I imagined him: broken and trembling and terrified and damaged, he was still headed somewhere, resilient not because he 
left his difficult life behind for something better, but because, like all of us, he carried the source and the history of his pain with him. The 
instruments of his suffering were also part of his survival. This, then, is how we all must—and do—live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I end this blog post, I’m going to get ready for a 10 mile bike ride; the last time I did this ride was three weeks ago.  After I get that done, I think I’ll start to get caught up on some chores that I’ve neglected over the last two weeks.  It’s time to continue.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="heart" /><category term="integrity" /><summary type="html">Over the last two weeks, I've been dealing with a depression flare-up. Having been aware of depression for half my life, I understand how I experience the condition. As a next step in this relationship, I'm sharing to exert ownership over this disease I live with.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Investing in Catholicism</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/faith/parenting/Investing-in-Catholicism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Investing in Catholicism" /><published>2022-02-19T19:15:59-06:00</published><updated>2022-02-19T19:15:59-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/faith/parenting/Investing-in-Catholicism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/faith/parenting/Investing-in-Catholicism/">&lt;p&gt;Throughout my childhood I struggled with fitting in.  As an Indian growing up the United States, I’ve always felt too Indian to be American and too American to be Indian.  That problem was particularly acute when I was growing up because I didn’t really understand who I was and what I found to be important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My parents for the most were un-religious.  While my mom grew up as a practicing Hindu, my dad grew up in a household that was mainly non-religious.  My dad’s experiences set the tone for our nuclear family and I recall awkwardly going to temple once a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I expressed to my dad that I was struggling with my identity in adolescence, he decided that it would be best to take me out of public school and send me to private school. To be honest, I think there’s a lot to be said about that: In her &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/talks/yuko_munakata_the_science_behind_how_parents_affect_child_development,&quot; title=&quot;The Science Behind How Parents Affect Child Development&quot;&gt;Ted Talk&lt;/a&gt;, Yuko Munakata points at that childhood development is complex and reflects environmental factors like friends and culture.  My dad was trying to immerse me in a culture that he saw as accepting, challenging, and successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The school indeed had a rich a culture with focused objective on nurturing students to “be a man.”  The culture was embodied through growth - academically, spiritually, and physically.  To facilitate that growth, the school provided experiences.  Religion class was mandated every year.  Monthly students attended an all school mass.  I even had the opportunity to participate in retreats with my fellow students.  By the time I had graduated from highschool, I had read the Bible cover to cover.  The spiritual environment helped me establish a north star even though I felt like I was misfit in the community.  It instilled in me the concept of objective truth that I could take with me and rely on regardless of situation and circumstance.  For me that guidance was critical part of learning to be comfortable with my own skin and my own values.  It provided a structure for me to think about loving God and loving other people; a way of exploring what the good life meant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, the school reaffirmed in many ways that I was a misfit.  I was one of the few minority students.  As a non-Catholic, I was one of the only students who didn’t approach the table to receive the Eucharist.  Through my education experience, I learned the importance of understanding detail and how that related to commitment.  In the context of faith, I learned how that agreement established norms and culture and how differences expressed in schism became important manifestations of belief:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How important is suffering to the human experience?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do you reconcile grace with works?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How important is community ritual?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found that community helped me think through my responses to these prompts.  More importantly, I found that community was accepting of people regardless of cultural or economic background.  Truly in God, misfits can unite in an effort to make the world better.  As I approached graduation, I expressed to my mom that I wanted to convert.  I think the idea of change and societal expectations frightened her.  For example, recently she voiced concern that I wouldn’t be able to participate in her funeral ceremony if I converted.  At the time, her response was to take me on a pilgrimage throughout South India to help me better understand my faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through that pilgrimage, I learned that faith within my extended family was deep.  Many members of the family explored religion to understand inequality, suffering, charity, and acceptance.  I learned to appreciate other questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How important is community?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How important is acceptance?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How important is sacrifice?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How important is individual ritual?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways it was beautiful experience.  Probably the most important thing I learned is that Faith could also unite people across distances as well as experiences.  I was able to relate to my family in ways that I hadn’t before.  That exploration gave me a new way of understanding my family across the world and provided an on-ramp to learn about relationships that I had otherwise felt strained or broken.  From that experience, I’m still in contact with nearly three quarters of my first cousins.  In addition to my faith, grounding myself in family has provided a foundation from which I’ve been able to build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;leading-faith-in-my-family&quot;&gt;Leading Faith in My Family&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having experienced the grounding affects of faith, it’s important to me that I can use it to center my family.  WHile the world gets smaller, I find my connections are spread further than they have been in the past.  As a family, we’ve moved twice.  My friends are spread across the world with concentrations in St. Louis, Minneapolis, San Francisco, Houston, Mumbai, Chennai, and Cochin.  I appreciate how easily my kids could feel like they are alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selecting a church has been an interesting process for me.  I don’t think there’s a faith that perfectly captures my relationship with God.  Likewise, I think there are many faiths that would offer unique opportunities to deepen that relationship.  With my wife, we ended choosing Catholic church because of the richness of community and balance between eastern and western religious thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The faith journey during the pandemic hasn’t been easy.  We’ve lost connection with our local church as we’ve avoided communion and faith formation to limit exposure.  In addition, the increasingly political stances taken by the Catholic church in the United States has compounded these feelings isolation.  In midst of this strife, I’ve also found embrace in shepherds who are ministering to a normally unchurched flock.  I find leaders like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/search/top?q=fr.%20james%20martin%2C%20sj&quot;&gt;Fr. James Martin&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gatewaychurch.com/staff/&quot;&gt;John Burke&lt;/a&gt; inspiring.  I’m grateful for their outreach as it as has provided a sense of connection during these times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we plan on returning to church, I’m looking forward to re-engaging with the local parish.  Ultimately, I think there’s enough room for me in a church with over a billion members.  In addition, as a member of the community, I feel like it’s important to be present in the effort to make church a respite for all who seek connection through faith.  Further, I think the rituals in the church reinforce things that I believe:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We believe in one God,&lt;br /&gt;
   the Father, the Almighty,&lt;br /&gt;
   maker of heaven and earth,&lt;br /&gt;
   and of all that is, seen and unseen.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
We believe in one Lord, Jesus Christ,&lt;br /&gt;
   the only Son of God,&lt;br /&gt;
   eternally begotten of the Father,&lt;br /&gt;
   God from God, Light from Light,&lt;br /&gt;
   true God from true God,&lt;br /&gt;
   begotten, not made, one in Being with the Father.&lt;br /&gt;
   Through him all things were made.&lt;br /&gt;
   For us men and for our salvation,&lt;br /&gt;
       he came down from heaven:&lt;br /&gt;
by the power of the Holy Spirit&lt;br /&gt;
   he was born of the Virgin Mary, and became man.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt; 
For our sake he was crucified under Pontius Pilate;&lt;br /&gt;
   he suffered, died, and was buried.&lt;br /&gt;
   On the third day he rose again&lt;br /&gt;
       in fulfillment of the Scriptures;&lt;br /&gt;
   he ascended into heaven&lt;br /&gt;
       and is seated at the right hand of the Father.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt; 
He will come again in glory to judge &lt;br /&gt;
       the living and the dead,&lt;br /&gt;
   and his kingdom will have no end.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
We believe in the Holy Spirit,&lt;br /&gt;
   the Lord, the giver of life,&lt;br /&gt;
   who proceeds from the Father and the Son.&lt;br /&gt;
   With the Father and the Son he &lt;br /&gt;
       is worshipped and glorified.&lt;br /&gt;
   He has spoken through the Prophets.&lt;br /&gt;
   We believe in one holy catholic &lt;br /&gt;
      and apostolic Church.&lt;br /&gt;
   We acknowledge one baptism &lt;br /&gt;
       for the forgiveness of sins.&lt;br /&gt;
   We look for the resurrection of the dead,&lt;br /&gt;
       and the life of the world to come.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Amen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="faith" /><category term="parenting" /><summary type="html">As a born Hindu and practicing Catholic, my faith journey has been complex. It's a core part of who I am. Likewise, it's a core part of how I'm trying to lead my family. As the pandemic becomes less dangerous, I'm looking forward to rekindling the relationship with the local faith community.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Diversification, Monitoring, and Real Estate. Oh My!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/investing/tech/Diversification-Monitoring-and-Real-Estate-Oh-My/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diversification, Monitoring, and Real Estate. Oh My!" /><published>2022-02-11T19:15:59-06:00</published><updated>2022-02-11T19:15:59-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/investing/tech/Diversification-Monitoring-and-Real-Estate-Oh-My</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/investing/tech/Diversification-Monitoring-and-Real-Estate-Oh-My/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;The Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I joined &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.responsive.org/manifesto&quot;&gt;ResponsiveOrg&lt;/a&gt; in 2015.  The group itself is an outreach of the work I was doing for Yammer.  It articulated a positive view of the future of work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Responsive Organizations are designed to thrive in less predictable environments by balancing the following tensions:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;table&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;More Predictable &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Less Predictable&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/thead&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Profit &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Purpose&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Hierarchies &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Networks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Controlling &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Empowering&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Planning &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Experimentation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Privacy  &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Transparency&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
  &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coalition shared examples of how organizations were trying to become more responsive through technology, engagement, and organization.  The reason organizations needed to change was tied back to do some work John Hagel and John Brown had done in 2010 called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://edgeperspectives.com/bigshift.html&quot;&gt;Shift Index&lt;/a&gt;.  They noted that since 1965, return on assets&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; had been steadily declining.  In contrast, over the same period employee productivity has been steadily increasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we are working harder, we are working on things that don’t matter.  More particularly, we are working on things that give us smaller incremental improvements rather than disruptive things that lead to step change outcomes.  There are many possibilities of why this is the case:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The more assets you have the harder it is to generate value.  When I graduated from college, our family had no assets.  The salary that I made was many multiples of the assets at our disposal.  As we started to build a nest egg, it became harder to sustain that growth because while we have more assets to put to work, I didn’t have more time to manage them.  Eventually, time becomes our most limited asset.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being human we have strong loss aversion which drives us to pay attention to the wrong things.  Rather than focusing on our most limited asset, we spend our time trying to drive a one or two percentage point increases on the stock market trying to eak out incremental improvements by being more productive.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What we measure is what we get done.  It’s easy to observe if we’re doing as well as the market, it’s much harder to observe if we’re working on the right things to lead to a Good Life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 2015, I started tracking my return on assets annually.  I wanted to understand if I was working on the right things financially.  From 2016 to 2020, I took hands on approach to managing my 401K while seeking an investment advisor to help me manage my money market accounts and IRA’s.  Over that period of time my 401K increased by 260% while the market grew by 168%.  The more assets you have the harder it is to generate value.  Masked in those returns is a significant portal of growth came from income.  For the last several years, I’ve maxed out my 401K investments and IRA contributions at $30K/year.  Since I’m now at the cap, reality has taken hold and my ROA forecasts are steadily declining.  I have to do something different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;smart-weighting&quot;&gt;Smart Weighting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, I was approached by &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcap.link/avinashsujee&quot;&gt;Personal Capital&lt;/a&gt;.  The investment philosophy that Personal Capital uses is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.personalcapital.com/wealth-management/smart-weighting&quot;&gt;Smart Weighting&lt;/a&gt;.  The basic premise is to identify invest equally in sectors that have unique characteristics and minimal correlation and then re-balance regularly.  As a result, a hot sector doesn’t become overweight because you sell more.  Likewise, a cold sector doesn’t become underweight because you buy more.  As a consequence of this approach, buying low and selling high is built into the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personal Capital will argue that this approach is better than buying low-cost ETF’s like ^SPY.  In order to audit that claim, I’ve tracked my annual returns on my investment accounts since 2020.  Over that period, my equity investment increased by 23% while the market increased by 21%.  In the prior period, my equity investments increased by 217% while the market increased by 33%.  I’ve netted that they are doing about the same of the market.  By leveraging them, I’ve been able to free up time which I’m primarily using to manage higher growth investments and passive income streams.  Ultimately, The only way I’m going to get close to returning to 217% growth over a two year period is by increasing the income I’m bringing in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning from Personal Capital - I’ve decided to view my nest egg as four major investment classes: retirement, equity investment, crypto, and real estate.  I’ve decided to make an active effort to try to balance my equity, real estate, and crypto investments.  The time I’m not using to manage my stocks, I’m now using to investigate new startups and technology trends.  If my forecast holds, I will have grown my passive income from $700 to $51,000 in five years.  My ROA will continue to be over 15% even while my assets double.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;real-estate-exposure&quot;&gt;Real Estate Exposure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While my passion for Crypto has been self-evident; I’m going to expound on my journey within real estate.  Over the last two years, real estate has been hot.  My home has appreciated by 200%.  Last year, I signed up for &lt;a href=&quot;https://statusmoney.com/?ref=KomJNO&quot;&gt;Status Financial&lt;/a&gt; to try to understand how I was spending my income in comparison to my peers.  It quickly stood out to me, that most of my peers had larger homes.  We’re happy with our house.  It’s a condo so we don’t spend much if any time on outdoor maintenance.  It’s in a great school district.  We don’t want to move.  Further, because our house is smaller we spend less on it.  We’ve been able to use those savings to fund a month long vacation annually as well as membership in a boat club which we use most weekends.  It works for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that real estate is tried and proven way to build wealth.  In order to increase my real estate exposure without buying a bigger house, I started looking at different real estate hedge funds.  I ended up choosing &lt;a href=&quot;https://fnrpusa.com/&quot;&gt;First National Realty Partners&lt;/a&gt;.  I picked them because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They primarily invested in Grocery Stores.  I don’t think Grocery Stores will be heavily disrupted by technology as proximity matters for freshness.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They let you specifically invest in a particular property; you could learn about the neighborhood they were investing in.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They are full service - their value chain includes finding, repairing, renting, and selling property.  They have expertise in the area as opposed to just being a financial play.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Their investments have some tax advantage as the repair costs are tax deductible and passed to investors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TLDR;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I’ll be able to hit my financial growth goals by keeping a smart weighting on equity, crypto, and real estate investments.  Ultimately, I think the proof will be in the pudding.  In the near term, I’m grateful that I’m able to do more work on the technological frontiers of our society.  If things do work out, I think I’ll be able to self-fund some charitable giving aspirations that I have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Return on assets is calculated as: &lt;img src=&quot;https://render.githubusercontent.com/render/math?math=ROA = \frac{Income}{Total Assets}&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="investing" /><category term="tech" /><summary type="html">I think I'll be able to hit my financial growth goals by keeping a smart weighting on equity, crypto, and real estate investments. Ultimately, I think the proof will be in the pudding. In the near term, I'm grateful that I'm able to do more work on the technological frontiers of our society. If things do work out, I think I'll be able to self-fund some charitable giving aspirations that I have.</summary></entry></feed>